<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of the state ecclesiasticall of this kingdome, in relation to the civill Considered vnder three conclusions. With a digression discussing some ordinary exceptions against ecclesiasticall officers. By C.D.</title>
            <author>Downing, Calubyte, 1606-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 218 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109839</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845483</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10388</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10388)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 955:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of the state ecclesiasticall of this kingdome, in relation to the civill Considered vnder three conclusions. With a digression discussing some ordinary exceptions against ecclesiasticall officers. By C.D.</title>
                  <author>Downing, Calubyte, 1606-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 98, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Turner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Calybute Downinge.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10388:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10388:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOVRS OF THE STATE ECCLESI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>STICALL OF THI <hi>Kingdome, in relation to the Civill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſidered vnder three</hi> CONCLUSION With a DIGRESSION diſcuſs <hi>ſome ordinary Exceptions againſt</hi> Eccleſiaſticall Officers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> C. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by WILLIAM TVRNER. 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10388:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10388:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE WILLIAM EALRE Of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Cranburne,</hi> Lord <hi>Cecyll</hi> of <hi>Eſendon,</hi> Knight of the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous order of the Garter, and one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt honourable Privie Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AY Jt pleaſe your honour to accept this preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as an acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Lordſhips favour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>your obſervant Chaplaine, Calybute Downinge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:10388:3"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 8. marg. <hi>for</hi> text, <hi>read</hi> tit. <hi>p.</hi> 15. marg. Clayman, <hi>r.</hi> Clapmar. <hi>p.</hi> 17. <hi>l.</hi> 15. with ſtate, <hi>r.</hi> with the ſtate. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 28. <hi>ſic ſtantibus, r. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantibus p.</hi> 35. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>ordinar. r. ordinario. p.</hi> 39. <hi>l.</hi> 1. adde <hi>à farlo. p.</hi> ib. <hi>Angliterra, r. Anghtlterra. p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> ib. 506. <hi>r.</hi> 56. <hi>p.</hi> 54. marg. <hi>Hallandes affaires. p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 8. Common, <hi>r.</hi> Cannon Law. <hi>p.</hi> 57. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>Conatus, r. Canutus. p.</hi> 59. marg. <hi>Francum, r. aerarium. p.</hi> 67. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>vacante pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentiſſimus, r. vacante; ſèd prudentiſsimus. p.</hi> 94. <hi>l. vlt. dele Othobone</hi> vpon.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="conclusion">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10388:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CONCLVSION I.</hi> That the preſent State Eccleſiasticall is moſt conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and beſt agreeing with the Civill.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith what care and coſt States and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, which vphold and deriue all happineſſe to man, as he is a ſociable and a feeble creature, ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, none will deny; eſpecially ſince they are ſo ſubiect to decay, and the cauſes of their corruptions ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Senec.</hi> 117.</note> For the beſt tempered common-wealth is not of any conſtant continuance, but full of changes, and thoſe at laſt, will after much interchange, driue it to a full and fatall period. It muſt therefore be the care of the preſent age, to ſee that it receiue no detriment while they are in it: for they may be ſo orderly, as to worke no diſtemper, but conſerue it in health and wealth, or at leaſt keepe it from decaying ſo faſt, that hauing ſome ſpace to fall in, it may recouer, or they haue time to leaue it, and not fall with it, nor that fall vpon them. Now the beſt, and all that the paſſing, preſent generation can doe, is either to keep things in primitiue order, or to reforme them to it. The firſt of which is difficult to continue, the other dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous if long diſcontinued. Yet Kingdomes muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10388:4"/> by the ſame meanes they were firſt eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. This labour, and care then will be to beſt purpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon thoſe parts which are moſt neceſſary, and vphold the reſt as eſſentiall and fundamentall, being the principles of the intrinſicall,<note place="margin">Polybius hiſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> originall good: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or vpon thoſe that ſecure theſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Now that which is the only infallible ground of theſe, muſt needs be princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally reſpected by thoſe that are vndertakers for the publick good; and that ground is true religion. For though ill manners are <hi>per accidens</hi> the cauſe, or rather the occaſion of making good lawes, yet they are better in the executing, beſt when they are obeyed. Now good manners cauſe obedience, and religion naturally begets good manners. But religion cannot ſubſiſt without pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke exerciſe and action, and ſo the requiſites of it are times, places, and ſome perſons who ought to be ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and wholly and only employed in it; and they muſt be in the common-wealth. Therefore ſeeing it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to haue a religion to preſerue the common-wealth, it is by conſequent as needfull, to haue preſervers of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that may not overturne the common-wealth by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ruling religion. Wherefore the choyſe of them need to be ſuch, that ſeeing they muſt be in the common-wealth of neceſsity, they may be of the common-wealth for vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal ſafety. And yet they are to be diſtinguiſhed by ſtate, and order, to avoyd confuſion; nor doth their diſtinction enforce any ſuch forme, after which they muſt governe, as may be inconvenient to the publicke civill ſtate, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are to be governed. The care then of the wiſeſt muſt be either to preſerue, or reſtore that forme of the Clergie, which is moſt agreeing with the Civill State, and that will be the meanes to prolong the age of the ſtate, by preſerving concord amongſt ſocieties; which, though at laſt it come to an end, yet it may out-laſt our dayes, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:10388:4"/> we be not vnhappy in the ruine; for it is not the infelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of States which haue long flouriſhed to decay, or be deſtroyed, but the vnhappineſſe of thoſe men, whoſe hap it is then to liue, and not when they did flouriſh. Now every form of a Clergie will not fit,<note place="margin">Guic hypor Poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but according to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers countries, they haue beene ſeverall, ſuiting to the times, places, and people. The firſt was the originall, domeſticall diſcipline in private families, before God made choyſe, and actually ſeperated a nation to himſelfe. Then followed the Leviticall Nationall regiment, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and compoſed of, and according to the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall and judiciall Lawes. Both theſe formes were not onely by divine permiſsion, but alſo by injunction; yet not perpetuall nor vniverſall. Neither of theſe then are the government wee muſt chuſe, becauſe that manner of exerciſing religion is antiquated. Wee muſt then conſider of a forme, which may be conformable to the preſent practiſe of true religion, in relation to Gods revealed Will, which may withall be ſuitable, and ſorting with this preſent ſtate, that ſo they may vphold each other; which forme, though it be not according to Gods ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe mandate in ſome particulars, yet it is not againſt it, but with his permiſsion of approbation in all points. Now in this choyce, wee muſt conſider our owne forme of Civill government, and whether that were impoſed vpon vs by conqueſt, or by our owne conſent; if by free conſent, and of long continuance, it will with more eaſe and deſire be preſerved, and with greateſt danger alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; if by conqueſt, the more Charters of priuiledges are granted to vs vnder it, the more it is endeared to vs, and eſteemed happy; but our forme of ſtate is a free Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, erected and protected by free conſent, and of long continuance, not impoſed but confirmed and reformed to the firſt freedome by a happy conqueſt, and endeered vnto vs by many Charters of wholſome priviledges.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:10388:5"/> Therefore we muſt ſeeke or keepe ſuch a forme of ſtate Eccleſiaſticall, as may beſt accord with our forme of Civill policie,</p>
            <p n="2">§. 2. This preſent State Eccleſiaſticall is the forme that beſt agrees with the Civill State. That it is not againſt the Law of God, I will not goe about to proue, becauſe I hope none will queſtion it: neither that it was the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue, and ſhould ſtill be the government of the preſent viſible Church, becauſe that is already proved without all contradiction by many moſt judicious and orthodoxe Divines: But my vndertaking is (as farre as God ſhall giue mee vnderſtanding) to diſcourſe, how it is moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable with this Kingdome. All States haue alwayes endeavoured, as to haue a religion, ſo to frame the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of it according to their owne diſpoſitions: but ſome with more doting indulgence, haue at laſt changed it into that which they were moſt naturally diſpoſed to, and did not alter and order their inclinations by it. As the foure grand Monarchies, the Chaldean with whom the Perſian may well be joyned, theſe turned the acts of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into philoſophicall conſiderations, enquiries, and explications of nature. The Egyptians (a principall branch of theſe Monarchies, and from whom ſome thinke the Chaldeans were derived, and that <hi>Belus Neptuni Libiae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que filius in Babyloniam colonos ex Aegypto traduxiſſet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diodorus Sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Biblioth. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; ex iis Sacerdotes quos Chaldeos Babylonii vocant, qui more Aegyptiorum astra obſervant, &amp;c.</hi>) Theſe Egyptians na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuperſtitious in religion, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in myſteries, transformed religion into all kinde of ſuperſtitions, and by trying concluſions and chymicall experiments vpon it, conceited the ſubſtance of it into vnexpected phanſies, furthered by mimicall expreſsions, leading into, and leaving in myſticall mazes. The Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians by nature <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, intelligent, able to find out, and loving to contend, drew religion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10388:5"/> into diſputes, and would beleeue no more than they could finde out by ſearch of reaſon, and apprehend by force of fanſie; and that they obſtinately maintained, by a wanton working wit, which they might with more eaſe doe, ſeeing their language was ſo happy for expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The Romans by nature inclined to dominion, fitted the frame of their religion to a Monarchicall forme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pontifices;<note place="margin">Cujaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Origin lis, <hi>§. 1</hi>
               </note> yet they ſeemed to ſeeke a Monopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of all the Gods in the world: (for they receiued and worſhipped the Gods of all the nations they conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.) Theſe nations framing religion to theſe ends,<note place="margin">Auguſt Civit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>20.</hi> cap</note> had a forme of government, vnder religious perſons, ſutable to further, contriue, and compaſſe by all meanes, their particular purpoſes, and therefore they gaue them power, of a moſt large extent, yea they were ruled by them; for the Chaldeans were originally Prieſts, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a prieſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Syneſiu</hi> 126.</note> and a Prince were all one with them. So the Magi amongſt the Perſians, the Prieſts of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphos</hi> amongſt the Grecians did what they would.<note place="margin">Pomp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Orig. I.</note> And the Romans were led by their Pontifices and Augures, but it was whither they would, namely to a Monarchy. Wee having not the ends of theſe nations in our religion, muſt not vſe the ſame forme of Clergie. For I conceiue the aime of the beſt and wiſeſt with vs, is to preſerue the Church and Common-wealth together. Now that cannot be, where the ſtate of the Clergie governs, but where it is governed. Our ayme being ſuch, let vs conſider what forme will be beſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned vnder this Common-wealth. There are but three diſtinct formes of Eccleſiaſticall government in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, as the Monarchicall, Ariſtocraticall, Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticall; of theſe, the Ariſtocraticall is moſt conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the rule of this Realme. In proving of which aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I will not onely inſiſt vpon the proofe of paſt and preſent experience, that it is ſo, but diſcourſe in reaſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:10388:6"/> why it ſhould be ſo. And firſt in oppoſition to the other formes of Eccleſiaſticall government: what they are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to produce, woefull experience hath long ſince felt in the one, and what we may expect, vpon probable conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, from the other, is not to be deſired by any that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and loue the happineſſe of this Civill State. For all their principles, fundamentall in their grounds, of augmentation in their growth, of conſervation in their heigth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Polybius lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> and of reparation in their decayes are moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for this Monarchy, and the cauſes of their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on would be ſo incorporated into the body and bowels of the Civill State, that if it fall not before them and into their hands, they would goe neere to pull it downe with them when they fall. Not ſo ſpeake of their power, which they muſt haue, and the exerciſe of it, either in an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and lawfull courſe, or by indulgence or vſurpation, and the manner of their proceedings in the execution of it, what inſtruments they vſe in counſell and action, how much they trench vpon the power, vndermine the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, countermine the proceedings, countermand the edict, and confront a Monarchy, I leaue it to wiſe and actiue men to conſider.</p>
            <p n="3">§. 3. Firſt to ſpeake of the Monarchicall, which is now the Papall government. How this Monarchicall forme hath heretofore agreed with this State, all know; and it is not likely that it ſhould now ſo well accord with it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the reaſons of that little agreement then, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent particular intereſt, in which this State vſed that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, are ceaſed; for then wee aymed to enlarge our dominion by the right of ſucceſſion in France, by the right of conqueſt in Scotland and Ireland. But the cauſes of diſagreement ſtill remaine, and are in their part ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated to an vtter oppoſition; ſo that as before it was dangerous, ſo now it is a deſperate caſe to re-entertaine that forme of Clergie, which can and will rule vs, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:10388:6"/> muſt neceſſarily alter, and ſo worke the ruine of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate. Vnder this forme this Kingdome was no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie, but a Province, vnder a forreiner, an vſurper and a tyrant. This was our beſt condition when that Clergie ruled vs, though as favourable as they could, or did any Monarchy in Europe. The lawes and priviledges of the land were continually broken and infringed by them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially thoſe lawes that did moſt immediatly vphold the Kings prerogatiue. Againſt them they continually promulgated particular edicts, for the decrees were too generall to be applyed to occaſions, and therefore they added the decretals, ſo called, becauſe they gaue wings to the decrees for quicker diſpatch. And wee ſhall finde,<note place="margin">Duare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> benefici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prooem</note> that moſt of the <hi>Decretall</hi> epiſtles, which concerne Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, were written to Engliſh Prelates. And (as I conceiue) ſome reaſon might be, becauſe the lawes of this land are more contrary to the Canon Law, than the lawes of any other States in Chriſtendome, being they are more ruled by the Civill Law, from which the Canon is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſo more cauſes might ariſe here amongſt vs, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the contrariety of the Lawes, or out of the narrower extent of the Common Law, and alſo partly out of the ignorance of the proceedings of this State, which was then likely to be moſt, becauſe intercourſe and intelligence with Rome for that time was abridged; (for <hi>Henry</hi> 2. being then at variance with <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> who was ſheltered by the Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not any Legate to reſide in the kingdome; but as ſoone as <hi>Vivian</hi> was arrived, he was queſtioned, and that by the Biſhops of Wincheſter and Ely, how hee durſt land without the Kings ſpeciall licence.) And partly they writ the oftner to Engliſh Biſhops, becauſe they ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them, and juſtly, to be more partiall for their Prince, than the Prelates of any other kingdome, as appeares by their readineſſe to examine this Legate, and alſo by an
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:10388:7"/> epiſtle <hi>Decretall</hi> of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib <hi>4.</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. <hi>17.</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <hi>7.</hi> qui filij legitimi. Sarisburienſis de nugis curial: lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>24</hi>
               </note> who then was <hi>Gilbert Foliot</hi> (a man much commended by <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> and <hi>Iohn Sarisburienſis</hi>) in that epiſtle hee curries favour with him in a cauſe which hee knew was of Eccleſiaſticall cognizance, and was ſo judged here in the Kings court, (as appeares out of <hi>Glanvill</hi> then Lord chiefe Iuſtice) I think in the very particular caſe.<note place="margin">Glanvill, lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi> Ad Regem An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae pertinet de poſſeſsionibus iudicare. Iohannes de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſijs contra Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifacium octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> But he feared, ſeeing the Biſhop could doe ſo much with the King, and would doe ſo much for his King, leaſt hee ſhould finde ſome way to entitle it to the Crowne: and hee had good reaſon to feare, ſince the Biſhop had ſo often in the Kings behalfe oppoſed <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Becket</hi> and him. Theſe may bee ſome reaſons why the Popes ſent ſo many epiſtles into <hi>England,</hi> and I am the more confirmed in them, becauſe I finde they were for the greateſt part written by the moſt Pragmaticall Popes, who buſied and beſtirred themſelves moſt in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up orders, and new freſh Fryes, and fraternities of Fryers; and in pulling downe the powers both of our Kings and Biſhops: to wit, from thoſe ſeaven Popes (who were the thirds; and I thinke the worſt of their names, I am ſure of their predeceſſors.) As for the moſt part they were written from <hi>Alex.</hi> 3. <hi>Lucius tertius, Vrbanus terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Clemens tertius, Coeleſtinus tertius, Innocens tertius,</hi> and <hi>Honorius tertius;</hi> theſe men did and undid very much, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were active and lived long. If then this forme of Clergie was thus prejudiciall to our ſtate before it was oppoſed and incenſed by the ſtatute of <hi>Proviſo</hi> and <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire,</hi> and caſt off by the Kings juſt re-aſſuming their power, (which ſhewes that all their right was nothing but our ſoveraignes wrong;) ſurely now wee are not to expect ſo much favour from them: and therefore as the State then thought it neceſſarie and right to caſheere it, and brought their purpoſe fully to paſſe; ſo it is now more neceſſary and juſt to keepe it out, ſince it is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:10388:7"/> increaſed in tyranny, ſince that unhappy, unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ill adviſed conventicle at <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">§. 4. Thoſe nations ſhall have the beſt uſe of that forme, who propound a civill ſtate as large as their Eccleſiaſticall; and to whom he hath firſt ſought too for aſſiſtance: and withall are able to overrule it. For after <hi>Iuſtinianus</hi> the laſt of the true <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the laſt of the good Popes, that See claue to <hi>Phocas;</hi> who named the Pope Vniverſall Biſhop, that hee might proclaime him Catholique Emperour. But when in the next Centurie the Eaſterne Emperours were infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with <hi>Saracens</hi> warre, began to pull downe images as ſome cauſe of the warres, which the Pope endeavoured to ſet up againe: then by the ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> whether becauſe they did him wrong in diſobedience, or rather becauſe they could doe him no good; the <hi>Greeke</hi> Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> fell off to the <hi>French</hi> before the next Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turie. And then <hi>Pipin</hi> uſed him to confirme, not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his new atchived Kingdome; for in thoſe dayes they gave no ſuch power, neither did Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> claime it: for hee depoſed not <hi>Childericke,</hi> but conſented to the depoſing, which was by the Peeres of <hi>France;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he ſet up <hi>Pipin</hi> in his roome: but they that depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the other onely ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> to have <hi>Zacharies</hi> adviſe in it,<note place="margin">Bulla <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> becauſe it might paſſe more plauſibly in the world by the conſent of ſo grave an Oracle: as it hath alway beene good wiſedome to winde in the conſcience of one who is eſteemed an upright Iudge, for the countenance of an unuſuall cauſe humorouſly undertaken by the firſt Author; eſpecially there being then a faction amongſt the Biſhops of <hi>France:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſo that this inquirie of his judgement in point of fact did non ſubmit to any claime of right. And <hi>Gotefridus Viterbrenſis</hi> affirmes, and <hi>Baronius</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>Francos non Zachariae paruiſſe decreto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed acquieviſſe conſilio:</hi> and there is great difference betwixt an abſolute
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:10388:8"/> injunction, and a politique adviſe, which is onely an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere out of diſcretion and left to diſcretion, implies no obligation of neceſſitie. But this is without queſtion, <hi>Pipin</hi> being ambitious of the Kingdome, and deſirous to cover and colour it with religious ends, uſed the Pope to countenance and compaſſe his deſigne; who would not withſtand him, being ingaged to him for protection and by bounty, or which is likelier, hee durſt not, being too much in his power. But howſoever it was, he clave faſt unto the <hi>French</hi> for that Century: eſpecially to <hi>Charles</hi> the great, the repairer of the Weſterne Empire; from whom the Caroline ſucceſſion continued till <hi>Otho</hi> the third. But then the <hi>French</hi> Kings being diſtracted by warres at home,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus de A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cona de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Papae: quaeſt. <hi>37.</hi> Art. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> could no more aſſiſt them: <hi>Gregory</hi> the fift an <hi>Almaine</hi> transferred it to the <hi>Almaines,</hi> choſe thoſe ſeaven Electors, but they agreed not well together: after the <hi>Almaine</hi> Pope was dead and <hi>Italians</hi> ſucceeded, they preſently began to quarrell with the Emperour, and to ſend challenges of right into <hi>Italy;</hi> knowing that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was not able to doe much for them in giving them as the <hi>French</hi> had done, and perceiving hee was more unable to hold from them that which they would have:<note place="margin">Segebertus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hron. paſſim.</note> ſo that the Emperours were continually imbroiled by them, being not able to rule them, decreaſing as faſt as they roſe. Then the oppoſition betwixt many particular Popes and Emperours, as betwixt <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeaventh and <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Alexander</hi> the third with <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke Barbaroſſa,</hi> was very ſtrong. But after it grew to ſuch a height that they were ſetled into factions of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, as the Eccleſiaſtiques and Imperialiſts, eſpecially in <hi>Italy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nabrigenſis hiſt. Anglicana lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> which the <hi>Italians</hi> quickly perceiving, becauſe earneſtly deſiring the Emperours power over them to be looſer, began to make uſe of the Papall preſent oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to procure their full liberty:<note place="margin">Abbas Vnſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis chron. paſsim.</note> and therefore theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions were moſt ſtrong there. Yet that grand faction
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:10388:8"/> diſtinguiſhed by many formalities, was principally main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained under the names of the <hi>Guelfs</hi> and <hi>Gibellins,</hi> which ſwallowed up all the private and pettie familie factions of <hi>Italie.</hi> As the <hi>Vrſini</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> were <hi>Guelfes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat hiſt. Ann</note> the <hi>Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi Gibellins,</hi> the <hi>Vberti</hi> in <hi>Florence</hi> were <hi>Gibellins,</hi> the <hi>Bondelmonti Guelfes,</hi> and ſo it was in <hi>Naples, Venice, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine:</hi> which ſtrife continued hot till <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, who perceiving how much his predeceſſors had gained upon the Emperour, and ſaw but little more for him to get; began to practiſe the like domineering humour upon the other Potentates of Chriſtendome, ſending his letters of claime to the Kings of <hi>France, England, Scotland, Denmarke, Poland, Hungarie.</hi> But being oppoſed by <hi>Philip le Beau</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> hee did flie backe to the Emperour for ſuccour, who then was <hi>Albertus,</hi> the firſt Emperour of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> (for though his father was Emperour, yet hee was not of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> neither of the old Marqueſſes nor late Dukes, but Earle of <hi>Hansburg,</hi> who had conquered the Dukedome of <hi>Auſtria</hi> for his ſonne.) This <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>Spaniard</hi> firſt began the faction betwixt the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> by giving the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Theſe two better agreed then any, becauſe the Pope had taken off the Emperour from ſeeking his owne right in <hi>Italie,</hi> by imploying him as his champion to enlarge his dominion in other Kingdomes: and partly becauſe the Emperour had good hope to continue the Empire in his familie, as it hath neere foure hundred yeares. From which time the Emperours and Popes diſagreements were not ſo frequent, but onely when ſome <hi>French</hi> favourers were Popes, and they ſate at <hi>Avinion,</hi> as <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the fifth with <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeaventh, and during the times of the Councels of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſill.</hi> But by reaſon of the ſchiſmes in the Roman See, they did one another neither much good nor harme, vntill the time
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:10388:9"/> of <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, a Spaniard, who was exactly ambitious, a great lover of his countrie, and one that did much for it.<note place="margin">Anonymus Hiſp. in vita Alex.</note> For hee joyned with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the firſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick King, helping him to ſubdue Spaine, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore firſt brought in the Inquiſition <hi>Contra los Iudios y mores, que le aviantornado Chriſtianos,</hi> which <hi>Caranza</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> conceived him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe bound in conſcience to vſe, by vertue of an oath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with an imprecation by one of his predeceſſours in the fourth Councell of <hi>Toledo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baronius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. An. <hi>637.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Baronius</hi> ſo much commends. This Pope alſo beſtowed vpon him the then diſcovered Indies, with many other favours, and for his ſake, and in oppoſition to the French, hee was as faſt a friend to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> as his deepe diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would ſuffer him;<note place="margin">Philip. Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noeus, lib. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and the rather, becauſe they had lately matched with the Houſe of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> which much weakned the French force, and ſtrengthned their factions.<note place="margin">Thuanus hist. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> But then moſt when <hi>Philip,</hi> the heire of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and <hi>Burgundie,</hi> incorporated himſelfe with Spaine. So that I will conclude theſe things conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that this forme is onely ſafe and convenient for thoſe kingdomes that propoſe conqueſts, and can rule it as the protectors of it.</p>
            <p n="5">§. 5. So then ſeeing this Clergie is not for vs, I will conſider of the other, which for diſtinct proceeding, we may call <hi>Democraticall.</hi> When the three Prime Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates of Chriſtendome, were <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, ſuch as deſerved and deſired to haue all the ſoveraigne power that could of right belong vnto them, and yet were contrariwiſe vſurped vpon, and deprived of all their eminent ſupremacie, in thoſe things that moſt concerned them; &amp; perceiving (ſome beginning to queſtion the Pope) a courſe of relieving themſelues, they began to vrge a Councell for reformation, not onely in doctrine and manners, but alſo in point of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:10388:9"/> government. But it was ſo long vrged by them, to no purpoſe, that <hi>Henry</hi> the eigth adviſedly wrote to the other; That ſeeing the Pope had ſo long put it off,<note place="margin">Hiſto. Trid.</note> and now intended to hold it within his owne territories, it were the beſt courſe for every one, to reforme his owne Kingdome, and he did ſo with the adviſe, conſent, and deſire of the Church and Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> repreſentatiue. No ſooner was a reformation in any degree ſetled, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it was excepted againſt by ſome that favoured the Church of <hi>Geneva,</hi> as not fully reformed, becauſe not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with their new neat platforme; &amp; that was vrged vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, as the only Apoſtolical government of the Church. But I marvell how ſuch an exact government ſhould be ſo ſuddenly framed, or elſe which is more ſtrange, that they could ſo conceale their happy invention; as that <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, a King of France, that ſearched into his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as much as any, ſhould not know of it. For I am very much deceived, if hee had not beene much miſtaken, knowing of this project, to deſire the Councell might be held at <hi>Geneva,</hi> being it was Diametrically oppoſite to the Romane. But our State had no reaſon to receiue it.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Trid.</note> For though it was neceſſary, not onely in reaſon of State, but alſo out of conſcience, that (after we perceived the indiſpoſition of the Romane Clergie to reforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, (which they ſeem to hold impoſſible.) For though every Cardinall takes an oath in the vacancie, yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not binde him when he is Pope; wee ſhould then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our duty, eſpecially ſeeing it ſtood with the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good.) Yet neither of theſe conſiderations did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage vs to accept of ſuch a forme of Clergie, as ſeemed to runne a cleane contrary courſe, ſeeing we propounded not an innovation, but a reformatioa; that being as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, as this was neceſſary, it could not here be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without an vniverſall innovation. Now all ſtirring changes are dangerous, eſpecially when the body of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:10388:10"/> common-wealth is full of diſeaſed, diſcontented hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. Becauſe all alteration ſets the humours a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and one humour being a-foote, ſtirs vp all the reſt, either alluring by ſympathie, or provoking by antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy; and when they are once a-foote, it is to be feared, that they will not onely disburthen the body of malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant oppreſſing cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ties, but weaken it in the moſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall parts, cauſing it to receiue a diſpoſition to the like diſtemper, vpon every ſmall diſtaſte. But it is moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to innovate in that part of a common-wealth, that is moſt eſſentially actiue, and hath beene lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, eſpecially if the matter propoſed doe miniſter any cauſe of relapſe. Both which ſeem too true in this new diſcipline, which gaue an occaſion to the Clergie to revolt in the denying the ſupremacie, which they lately acknowledged. And being a forraine French deviſe, might ſeeme to come within the compaſſe of a <hi>praemunire</hi> for intruſion. as well as that of the Church of Rome for vſurpation. But this was only propounded, not brought in, and that by men who were by ſome beleeved to be faithfull to our State. And it may be, they had no dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous aime in it, yet it would haue beene very dangerous for our kingdome, ſince it did neceſſarily induce an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the profeſſion and practiſe of the lawes, which by reaſon of their long vſe, are as it were naturalized, into the manners and diſpoſition of our nation. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhetor. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap: <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> It muſt neceſſarily haue conferred ruines vpon our ſchooles of learning and hoſpitals of charity, razed the foundations of our Churches, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded diviſions of pariſhes, changed the right and cuſtome of paying tythes, with many ſuch miſerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences, which were ſo in the Apoſtles times of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, in perſecution. So that the State then would not venture to trie concluſions vpon it ſelfe, by this new receipt, <hi>but choſe rather to feele the ſuppoſed paine, than to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:10388:10"/> take the pill:</hi> and yet it hath ſubſiſted, though not in that heigth of health, which that forme of government pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; yet in ſuch a good competent continuance of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable well, that the preſent ſtate alſo had rather indure the worſt of the diſeaſe, than make the beſt vſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie. And if it muſt haue made ſuch a change in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, what would it haue done in the continuance? how would it haue agreed with this Monarchie, that muſt haue entred with ſuch oppoſitions? ſo that I neede not to ſay much to diſcard it, for it hath enough in it at the firſt ſight to keepe it out. And I confeſſe, that if I would, I cannot ſay much of it with any confident certainty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe indeed I doe not know, neither doe I thinke that any of them doe, or at leaſt ever haue ſet downe, in poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and plaine termes, the whole frame and face of this platforme, as they would haue it received in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But as much as I conceiue of it, and at the beſt and pureſt, it is a mixt Democraticall diſcipline, and it is not likely, that a diſſolute Democracie ſhould long agree with this Monarchie. It is not my intent here to diſcourſe of the nature of a Democracie,<note place="margin">Clayn Arc.</note> that I ſhould ſhew the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold conſequent, coincident inconveniences, that doe naturally flow in with it, and follow it (notwithſtanding that <hi>Machivell</hi> in many of his diſcourſes vpon <hi>Livie,</hi> doth preferre a Democracie before any other forme, but rather wittily, out of a Paradoxicall contradicting hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, than wiſely, out of the weight and worth of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſage, and ſerious arguments. And <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith thus much for it, in his <hi>Idaea</hi> of a Common-wealth,<note place="margin">Plat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inter iniquas formas optima, inter legitimas deterrima.</hi> For if it begin to degenerate into an Ochlocratie, (as I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it poſſible, but it muſt, conſidering that liberty is the end and excellencie of it) then it turnes to a moſt head-ſtrong, intollerable tyrannie. For I am not of their opinion, that hold it a contradiction, that where a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:10388:11"/> prevayles, there can be a tyranny. For the <hi>Ephori</hi> of Sparta, were as the Tribunes of the people of Rome, choſen by the people, and out of the common people, and the conſervators of their liberty. Yet I thinke there are but few that diſcourſe of theſe <hi>Ephori,</hi> but they conclude, and condemne their government of tyranny. They caſt <hi>Pauſanias</hi> into priſon, and <hi>Thucidides</hi> ſaith, that they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped that power over, and againſt their Kings, for they put <hi>Agis</hi> junior to death,<note place="margin">Plato de leg. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Plato,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and they were ſet vp to reſtraine their Kings. It is a hard matter to keepe that liberty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its limits, in any common-wealth, where it hath the ſupreme government, and therefore with much difficulty will it ſubmit to be governed by a free Monarchy, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a Democracie of that new nature, which makes the ſame perſons civill ſubjects, and eccleſiaſticall ſuperious, thoſe lay Elders that are neither Miniſters nor Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and yet muſt be governours in the Church, whoſe juriſdiction doth deſtroy the nature of a Monarchie. For all publick government in the Church, derived from Chriſt, the fulneſſe of it, is either Propheticall, Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, or Regall; and they aſſume not any of theſe, but the Regall, which is given in charge to ſupreme Chriſtian Magiſtrates in a Monarchie; and therefore, if they deriue not this power from him, they eſtabliſh a regiment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. So that if his power, doth not include theirs, they exclude his; and he having no ſupereminent power over them, as they impeach his right, ſo they will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large their owne liberty, till it be diſſolved into a looſe licentious libertiniſme:<note place="margin">Polybius hiſt. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as <hi>Polibius</hi> well expreſſes it.) And if they did not thus, it were the greater vertue, ſeeing they muſt haue ſuch power limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by lawes left to diſcretion. And they would finde it a hard peeece of patience, to abſtaine and containe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within ſuch bounds of obedience, as this State
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:10388:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> neceſſarily requires. Can men that profeſſe themſelues popular paſſe plauſiblie and pleaſe the vulgar if they doe not to their vtmoſt vphold them in their higheſt inſolencies?<note place="margin">Tull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Agra</note> 
               <hi>Tullie</hi> found this impoſſible when as hee withſtood the people in <hi>Lege Agraria,</hi> for they caſt him off, and clave to <hi>Rullus,</hi> who would be <hi>popularis</hi> though it were but in <hi>populatione:</hi> and as it cannot ſtand with the power of our government, ſo it withſtands the honour of our governour, debaſing the majeſtie of a Monarchie into a popular paritie, without reſpect of His moſt ſacred perſon. In this it is truly Democritall; for as it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for libertie, ſo it muſt bee vpheld by equality: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot be fully free without <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Poly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>6</hi>
               </note> and I cannot then conceiue how any could apprehend it as a forme likely to agree with ſtate; ſo that this government at the beſt would bee like the ſpleene in the body, which is the ſubject of the dregs and ſettlings of the humours, as a Democracie is <hi>la feccia della plebe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hiſt.</note> and as the ſpleene being not able to mooue it ſelfe is not troubleſome, ſo long as it is not preſſed vpon by the heart, but permitted full and equall liberty, nor diſturbed by a <hi>Flatus hypocondria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but once mooved <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> affectes the head and heart with turbulent diſtempers;<note place="margin">Hipp notio</note> ſo in a Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracie as long as they haue all at their looſe liſt, and are not compelled to keepe within compaſſe, but apprehend themſelves equall to the higheſt in all reſpects, and are not mooved by ſome ſedicious ſpirit, they are quiet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; <hi>Nam multitudo, ſicut mare, per ſe immobilis eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Livi</hi> Pſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> but if once they perceive that any goe about to oppreſſe or croſſe them in their falſe and fugitive liberty (as they are very ſuſpicious vpon the leaſt cauſe) they preſently are ready, but <hi>tentare magis quàm tueri libertatem:</hi> and if any one dare but begin to blow a Trumpet of ſedition, (as they doe not eaſily) <hi>ſtatim ferox erit ſi non ad bellandum,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:10388:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſaltem ad rebellandum.</hi> I doe confeſſe that this forme of government may bee of good uſe in ſome ſtates at ſome times, as in a popular ſtate where theſe Lay Elders may be both Church and Citie Burgeſſes; as the Democraticall <hi>Helvetians</hi> approved it: ſo alſo as for the enlarging of a Monarchie,<note place="margin">Machivellus, l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> the Monarchicall is beſt; ſo for the ſettling of a Monarchie, that Democreticall may be ſafeſt, and ſo may bee the beſt government when a ſtate is not ſettled but newly erected: for then it is not ſafe to uſe ſeveritie a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when our ſtate was not fully ſettled. <hi>Martin Mar-Pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>late</hi> dared to vent his diſcontented humours in ſalt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,<note place="margin">Curtius Hiſtor. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> as men in rheumes: <hi>In novo &amp; precario imperio no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatim jugum rigidum cervici imponendum,</hi> but it is good taming them by degrees, for then a Magiſtrate hath little power to command, much leſſe to reſtraine; &amp; therefore it hath bin found the beſt courſe to let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take their courſe: for <hi>Mos eſt vulgo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus Hiſtor. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Livius lib. <hi>11.</hi> Hiſtor.</note> 
               <hi>mutabili ſubitò, &amp; tam prono in miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam, quàm immodicum ſaevitiâ fuerat,</hi> and ſo by indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence finde <hi>laſcivire magis plebem quàm ſaevire.</hi> And <hi>I am perſwaded that this diſcipline was onely choſen for that time when the Apoſtles were under perſecution,</hi> and there were no Chriſtian Magiſtrates to repaire to for juſtice: then they appointed ſome to judge betwixt brother and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But it doth not appeare that they were Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iudges, certainly no ſuch lay Elders in the Apoſtles times as the Separatiſts now plead for, but rather civill ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters to make agreement betwixt them in civill contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.4.5. <hi>Hiſtor. Con. Trid. lib.</hi> 3.</note> (as may appeare out of the place) though the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Hiſtory <hi>Concil. Tridentini</hi> make that a ground for Epiſcopall juriſdiction. For the Apoſtles had no reaſon to delegate the cognizance of ſpirituall cauſes, becauſe in thoſe dayes they were ſo few, and needed no proofe to them; becauſe they had the gift of diſcerning of ſpirits, and of knowing of ſecrets, hauing the gift of prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And I doe not beleeue that it can bee proved that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:10388:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> they gaue commiſſion to any to receiue accuſations, (which is much leſſe then to giue judiciall cenſures and deciſions) to any but to the Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tit</note> but I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to enter into controverſies, neither need I, ſeeing ſo much hath beene already written in that point to good purpoſe by many moſt reverend Fathers of our Church. But to returne to my intended diſcourſe; this ſtate of the ſoveraigntie of theſe ſeniors I grant to be of ſome uſe in free Cities in time of tumult; and ſo I doe beleeue M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> intended it, yeelding to a popular partie, and not as an vniuerſall perpetuall government for all truely reformed Churches. For though ſuch a wiſe reſpected man as hee was, might during his time preſerue it in the ſame corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent conformitie to his propoſed patterne, (as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libius</hi> ſaith) the <hi>Thebane</hi> Democracie <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; it ſtood not by the good temper of their pollicie,<note place="margin">Polyb</note> but by the vertue of their governours <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: ſo might it bee ſaid of the <hi>Geneva</hi> Church government, that though for the tranſgreſſion of it many were the rulers of it, being a Democracie:<note place="margin">Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nil m prodeſt curari lunt. Senec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet by a man of underſtanding and knowledge, the ſtate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was prolonged; for hee could doe much to appeaſe ſeditions, as <hi>Franciſcus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Volterra</hi> ſooner ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled a tumult in <hi>Florence</hi> by his graue preſence, then the Magiſtrates could by the weight of their authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. It is plaine then out of this that hath beene ſpoken, that this government by popular Presbyterie is not for this ſtate.</p>
            <p n="6">§ 6 Neither of theſe being convenient, and there is but another, and it hath alwayes beene the government in this ſtate; it muſt neceſſarily follow without any more proofe, that this is moſt agreeable with the Civill. Thoſe that are no well willers to our ſtate haue ſtrucke at our Church gouernment, with which there is ſuch a happie hartie vnitie, as dare bid the world doe as ſhee would bee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:10388:13"/> done to (as that abſolute Statſe-man the Earle of <hi>Salisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> replyed.) And it is no marvell, ſince it is not onely the primitiue ancient government of the Church in generall; but the onely forme alſo that euer was received in this ſtate, according to the ancient lawes of this Iland, though it ſeeme to be brought in under <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, when it was onely reformed from the euils, and reſtored to the former ſtate: for our Clergie was never of right ſubject to the Pope, neither as he was Patriarch to the Weſt, nor in his province. And this Ariſtocraticall forme hath moſt happy qualifications that diſpoſe it to the peace, profit, honour, &amp; ſafety of this ſtate: I could now wiſh with <hi>Tully</hi> when hee was to write againſt <hi>Democraticall Agrarian</hi> lawes,<note place="margin">Ad Atticum, l. <hi>2.</hi> epiſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vtinam Theophraſtum</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Vbi multa ſcribuntur</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. After this Kingdome with many others had long laboured under a lingring conſumption, being continually ſucked, and in a manner exhauſted by the continuall ſupplying of the Popes Exchequer, which drew away the vitall ſpirits, weakned the ſinewes of warre; cauſing extenſions and convulſions: and farther alſo in reſpect of domeſtique peace, it had not a juſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of power to exerciſe its onely civill and lawfull authority: inſomuch that many who ſhould have knowne what in poſſibilitie of ſtate might bee done for a recovery of a temporalitie, diſtempered and diſtreſſed by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant humerous power of an uſurped ſpiritualitie, like a feaver in the ſpirits cauſed by obſtruction;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hippocrat: lap. <hi>5.</hi> prog.</note> All thoſe men gaue it over for deſperate, ſome conceiving the diſeaſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable in its owne nature, becauſe, that <hi>non obſtante</hi> the helpe of ſo many ſtrong ſtatutes and purging proviſoes, the diſtemper was as violent, and more virulent then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; &amp; they ſaw no ſafe and certaine courſe of preventing phyſick, for it was ſo far ſpent, as that it ſeemed to haue paſſed the period of curing: but as when men are brought to a deſperate point they will trie concluſions, and they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:10388:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> that drive them to it doe often repent it; ſo the Pope put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and paſſing our ſtate upon deſperate hazards, forced it to trie its ſtrength, which is ſoone found; neceſſitie driving, and opportunitie drawing: <hi>Acerrima virtus eſt, quam ultima neceſſitas extundit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a men. l</note> and ſo it caſt ſuch an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable vnruly rider, who thought, and ſo did all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, that hee had ſitten cloſer and faſter upon our skirts, and would not beleeue that it was poſſible for a Parliamentary power repreſenting the ſtate, euer to haue beene able to diſſolue the great Abbies, though they durſt fully reſolue it; untill they ſaw them begin with the little ones; then they had reaſon to grant it poſſible:<note place="margin">Ariſt. R lib. <hi>2.</hi> c</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Yea they found it fully finiſhed, and that on ſuch a ſudden, that as it wrought admiration in the beholders, ſo it procured ſafety to the actors. For in actions of that nature, haſte onely makes good ſpeed. That the event of this action was good, is proved by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the ſtate. But for the action in it ſelfe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, as I doe not commend it, ſo I will not condemne it, becauſe I am not able to ſift and ſearch into the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of it; but I will onely ſay thus much of it, That actions that ayme at, and make great alteration, though to the beſt, doe ſeldome keepe a juſt mediocrity, eſpecially in reſpect of that part of the common-wealth, which is the ſubject of the alterations: as a ſtrong, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Chymicall</hi> ſpirit-purge doth in a naturall body, that ſtirres vp more than ſhould be moved, and purges out good, as well as ill humours. But no ſooner was our State thus delivered from vnder the tyrannie of the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Monarchy, but it as ſoone pitched vpon the Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craticall government, as ſuitable and fitting beſt with the weale-publick. And as all the Chriſtian world did then in ſincere judgement of State <hi>rebus ſic ſtaantibus</hi> approue their choyce, ſo we haue ever ſince found the happy ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it, in the ſafety, honour, and treaſure of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:10388:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> State. Conſider it firſt, how it wrought little or no alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in the receiving, being according to the lawes, taken by their owne choyce, reſtrayned with the limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Civill State. For all the turmoyle and toſſing tumult, was onely in caſting out the other forme, as a privation, before the induction of a new forme in natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bodies. It was received without force, as moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to the Civill State, and no other could haue beene brought in with ſuch certaine good ſecurity of the ſtate: for the Monarchicall that time could not be received,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Concil. Trid. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> but either vpon their repentance of what they had done, and by procuring of a pardon from the Pope, (as it was in Queene Maries dayes: and doe but conſider, how evill that was for the State) or elſe by helpe of forraine force joyning with domeſtick rebellion, as was often attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted. But this was not any thing ſafe for the kingdome, as is already proved. And for the Democraticall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, there was great and certaine danger in receiving of that, for it could not poſſibly be conceived to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, but with a ſchiſmaticall ſedition, ſince it was approved but by a faction. Now doe but conſider, how dangerous ſeditions are in an ancient kingdome; if it were now a ſettling, happily the vigour of youth would beare it out, as one maine reaſon (as I conceiue) why the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Monarchy was not ruined by thoſe foure firſt grand ſeditions, was becauſe it was but <hi>ſecunda aetas, &amp; quaſi adoleſcentia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lucius Florus lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> But when a State is growing old, ſeditions are deſperate courſes to procure changes, though it be for the beſt. For though the events of them be but doubtfull, yet the deciding-place is certaine of loſſe. But for this preſent forme, as it re-entred without a State-earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, without any ſhaking of the ground of the Civill government, ſo it hath ever continued peaceable, and a pacifier of growing differences, being the middle State of three, carrying it ſelfe as a moderating mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:10388:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the King and the Subjects. And all this good, and much more proceeds from the temper of the forme of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. For it is the onely forme fit to be vnder this Monarchy, becauſe it will onely be eaſily ruled and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the State, when as both the other will rule wher they are entertained, although after a divers manner; one having dominion over the Civill, the other without it. But this is vnder the Civill, in relation to the head; and in it, in relation to the body. And as it is eaſily ruled, ſo it will not eaſily be diſordered, as the other will, though they ſhould ſubmit to be ruled for a time, till they be able to reſiſt. For ambition is ſo perniciouſly provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that it will be ſomething able to reſiſt the power of its oppoſite, to get from vnder it, before it trie to goe about it. Firſt, taking care not to be oppreſſed, before it endeavour to oppreſſe; for all the branches of rebellion, are rooted and hid in the depths of diſſembled diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But this is not ſo inclined; for if any forme of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie degenerate, it muſt be either into a Tyranny, an Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy, or a diſſolute Ochlocraty. Now an Ariſtocracie cannot be immediately diſſolved, either into a tyranny, or a tumultuous popularity. And it is not eaſie to conceiue, how it ſhould by any meanes, by the courſe of State cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ever degenerate into a head-ſtrong popularity of it owne accord, without externall force. And as little reaſon there is, why this ſhould advance it ſelfe to a tyranny, by turning the Church into a court,<note place="margin">Earle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bury hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to ſcan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> papers.</note> and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion into a vaſſall to ambition; for it muſt be reduced and reſtrained into an Oligarchie: and there is no great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in this point, to feare the Clergie in this kingdome, all things conſidered. It is true (as all Hiſtorians and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks obſerue) that an Ariſtocracie is ſubject and prone to be corrupted into an Oligarchie: But doe but obſerue the end of an Oligarchie, and you will finde, that an Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracie can haue no ſuch ayme; for their end is, to grow
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:10388:15"/> rich, as the States of Venice and the Belgick provinces, and their counſels driue at that end,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and according to this end, and this counſell to it, he that will prevaile in perſwading with them, muſt deliberate,<note place="margin">Sen. Suaſor. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in libera civitate, non vt apud reges, quae dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant, ſed quae proſunt ſuadenda ſunt.</hi> But our Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Ariſtocracie is not to be ſo perſwaded, having no ſuch counſels, becauſe not the ſame end; only they may be rich, if they did deſire it, becauſe being poore, they are a fit ſubject of wealth. The poverty of this Clergie hath charmed it againſt actiue ambition, ſo that one of the <hi>Optimates</hi> doe not looke higher than his peeres, ſet with him in equall power and honour, in relation to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Dioceſſes, though the power of juriſdiction be in ſome caſes larger, in the provinciall Prelate, <hi>Nemo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum Epiſcopum ſe Epiſcoporum eſſe dicit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſtinus contra Donat. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>neque tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co terrore ad obſequendi neceſsitatem, collegas ſuas adigit:</hi> ſo that <hi>per accidens,</hi> the impoveriſhing of the Clergie in <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, when it ſeemed in the eye of ſome too rich for the Civill State, did this good, to preſerue them from an Oligarchie; even as to take ſo much bloud away in a pluriſie, as to bring a man to a deepe conſumption, is a probable preſervatiue againſt dying of a burning feaver. So that alteration of this State is not much to be feared, in reſpect they haue no reaſon to alter it; and withall it is not eaſily altered, if they had this or any other ground to doe it. For an Ariſtocracie in it ſelfe conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, is a government of a moſt conſtant, continuing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, eſpecially, when it is mixed and tempered with a Monarchy. For the reaſon of its conſtancie is not onely the ſlowneſſe of the motion, either to augmentation or diminution, like a great engine moving with many joynts, in which poynt a Monarch will much advantage in advancing &amp; ſetting faſter forward, if not their delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, yet their determinations; and with eaſe and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:10388:15"/> ſpeed ſtay all their errors and declinings, while they are but in the breedings, beginnings, and begettings; but then alſo the force of their factions (which breaking out, are the common ruine of Ariſtocracies) will be abated, as it may be ſeene in the Spartane and Venetian States, oppoſed to the Athenian and Florentine. For theſe had an Ariſtocracie without a Monarchie, and were continually toſſed with ſeditions and factions. As that long laſting faction of the <hi>Guelfes</hi> and <hi>Gibilines,</hi> which could never be fully taken away, but by the ruine of one partie, when as the Venetians their neighbours (whoſe Duke was then not a <hi>Simulachrum imperij</hi>) kept the faction out of their common-wealth, though they did declare themſelues ſometimes on one ſide, and ſometimes on another, leſt they ſhould haue beene hated of all, as negligent neutrals; but they did not nouriſh the faction amongſt themſelues, but maintained it in other Countries, as they would doe warres. But the State of <hi>Millaine</hi> could never be free from it, vntill it was extinguiſhed by <hi>Franciſco Sforza,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paulu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiſt. lib</note> (who was a free Prince, though an vſurper) ſo that the mixture of a Monarchy, and the predominancie in an Ariſtocraticall State, doth not onely make it actiuely more able to offence, but more paſſiuely powerfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue, not onely by preventing preſervations from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick dangers, but alſo by recovering it out of them. <hi>And our preſent State Eccleſiaſticall is thus mixed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar ſumm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> (for I doe not vrge a ſtrict Ariſtocracie; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as Ariſtotle) and therefore hath the beſt meanes of conſervation in reſpect of the forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And it hath one more prevalent preſervatiue in the Optimates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, which is, that they are ſtrongly diſpoſed to this kinde of government, not onely by being of quiet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templatiue natures, but alſo Academicall Colledge go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which doth firſt poſſeſſe them and fully pleaſe them, is Ariſtocraticall, having the proper ayme of that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:10388:16"/> forme of government;<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, diſcipline according to law, is the end of that forme of government. And they then that ayme at that, are moſt likely to preſerue it, by perſevering in their intentions; when as others that will deviſe new platformes, and platforme diſcipline, and will ſeeme wiſer than the lawes, doe ſuddenly ſubvert or diſturbe this moſt ſafe and ſetled forme of government.<note place="margin">Thucydides l. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Witneſſe the Athenians and the Florentines, who being of a ſtirring over-actiue temper, and alwayes doing, though it were to the vndoing of things well done, changed this forme of State ſeven times, which corrupting tranſmutations, I hope <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chivell</hi> their Countryman doth not call and commend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the termes of reformation,<note place="margin">Machivellus lib <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and reduction to their primatiue principles, without he will grant their prime originall order, to be rayſed out of confounded confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. When as the Venetians, who haue beene calme and cold, and conſtant in provident proceedings, haue kept to the ſame forme without any fundamentall alterations, and that becauſe they will be ruled by lawes; whereas the Florentine is ſo overweeningly wiſe, that he thinkes he ſhould Emperour-like rule and make lawes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> So that <hi>Bodinus</hi> judgement of them, and the Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans is true; and approues him to be a moſt rationall ſtatiſt;<note place="margin">Bodinus de repub. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dignos ſe eſſe imperio ſinguli arbitrentur ad populare imperium, magis quàm Optimatum inclinati.</hi> But ſuppoſe this government ſhould be diſordered, it is eaſilieſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed againe, which is a point of very great ſafety, it may be done without any ſtirrs of tumults, and ſpeedily, for it hath not that power to reſiſt authority, which the other two formes haue; and that becauſe it vſeth not the meanes they doe to procure it. For the Monarchy of the Church of Rome, and the Democraticall diſcipline, ſtirre vp the vulgar, and rely and reſt vpon them for aſſiſtance, and defence, and therefore they endeavour to wooe and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:10388:16"/> win their hearts, that they may vſe their hands and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: yet they doe it divers wayes. As the Romaniſts, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many other wayes, they get into their hearts at their eares by auricular confeſſions, they hold them by their eares, and by their eyes; they faſcinate their fond phantaſies with ſuperſtitious ceremonies, exquiſitely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, full of myſticall and magicall mazes, broached by fancie, continued and countenanced by fables, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the maſſie materiality of bodily exerciſe, as may be ſeene in the auſterity and State of an Auſtrian penance, or in a Pontificall proceſſion, where all is done with ſuch concealed ſecrecie and ſilence, that nothing is proſtituted to be polluted by the vnſanctified view of the vulgar. Thus by feare mixed with delight in ſuperſtition, they can leade them as they liſt, and engage them in their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and bequeath to them their dangers they haue pulled vpon themſelues. The Diſciplinarians are not onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deered to them, for the forme and frame of their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for their novelty, but they make vſe of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition alſo to hold them, and to haue them at their beck; but in a courſe cleane contrary to the other, for they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe all the other haue done, in point of ceremony, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſideration, whether it be good or bad and that out of a ſuperſtitious rage, as the other did out of feare: (for ſuperſtition is grounded vpon either of thoſe paſſions.) And as their feare was mixed with pleaſure in the end, ſo theirs is mixed with profit, when in the deſtroying of ſuperſtition they enrich themſelues with the ſpoiles, and ſaue charges in ornaments. Which profaneſſe of theirs, is in ſome reſpects worſe than their ſuperſtition, and it many times ends in Atheiſme. For though they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated after a falſe manner, yet they were dedicated and devoted to the true God, and ſhould not be profaned to common vſes, but ſanctified by a new and true conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as well as the Churches wherein they were. Thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:10388:17"/> thoſe formes of Church-government haue power to withſtand the reforming rod of authority. But our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State vſeth no ſuch meanes to ſtand out a rebellion, becauſe if it offend, it rather proceeds out of weakneſſe than wickedneſſe, from ſcholaſticall indiſcretions, that deſerue rather pitty than puniſhment. For it is not likely, that they would diſturbe the State, who ſhall certainly loſe that little they haue by it, rather than get more. I find, that amongſt thoſe Prelates that haue troubled and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyled kingdomes, <hi>Peters</hi> pretended ſucceſſours haue only gained, by fiſhing in ſuch troubled waters. And as they can haue no end worth their ſtirring, ſo their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination is not ſo perniciouſly pragmaticall, they are farre from the tricks of tumbling projecters, and all actions proceed either from our generall end, or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar inclination; and this inclination is fortified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, if not formed and framed by their ſtudies, which haue a great influence into the diſpoſition. I haue not in this diſcourſe, entred much into the commendation of an Ariſtocracie in generall, preferring it before a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, partly becauſe I feare, leſt ſome ſhould ſerue me as <hi>Caſtellanus,</hi> a French Phiſolophy reader (who, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, was <hi>Ramus</hi> his Tutor) ſerved his antagoniſt <hi>Bigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi> For when <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt was deſired by ſome of his Nobles, to reade <hi>Bigotius</hi> his Diſputations, <hi>Caſtellanus</hi> told his Majeſtie, he was an <hi>Aristotelian,</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> preferred an Ariſtocracie before a Monarchie,<note place="margin">Thuanus, hiſt. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> &amp; ſo tooke off the Kings affection from him. But he might be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, becauſe I doe not beleeue it was <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but his policie, to diſſwade all others from affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting it, that his Maſter <hi>Alexander</hi> might effect it. But I did purpoſely forbeare it, becauſe it was not my propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that an Ariſtocracie is ſimply a more convenient forme of State than a Monarchie; but that this Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is more convenient for this State at this time, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:10388:17"/> that it was received with an vniverſall conſent and deſire of all, and hath its right according to the lawes; is moſt eaſily ruled by them, not eaſily nor ſuddenly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed or diſturbing; and moſt eaſily reformed if it bee diſordered: ſo that I may now vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably conclude, that the preſent ſtate Eccleſiaſticall is moſt convenient and beſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the Civill.</p>
            <div type="digression">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:10388:18"/>
               <head>A DIGRESSION DISCVSSING Some ordinary exceptions againſt Eccleſiaſticall Officers.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough none bee more loath and fearefull to come within the liſts of controverſies; yet ſeeing all that I haue already poſitiuely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed, is not onely controverſed but alſo contradicted by theſe exceptions; I reſolved to diſſolue and diſpell them, leaſt they ſhould by a darke reflexion cloud my cleare proceeding. And I am not a little confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced in my purpoſe, when I conſider whoſe cauſe it is that I vndertake, even the moſt able advocates of the Church, ſuch powerfull pleaders as are infallibly ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to defend both their cauſe and mee their poore defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant; for they are abſolutely able (if their conſcience would but diſpence with their vnderſtanding) to make a bad cauſe if not good, yet to put it in a good caſe by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it plauſible, ſo that I am encouraged to vndertake it with this conſideration; that where I am found weake and wanting, they are ſufficient and ready to ſuccour and ſupply; if they ſhall apprehend the exceptions perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and pertinent, and any impeachment to their practiſe and power. As they that haue made triall of their ſtrength haue found,<note place="margin">D. Couzius his apology for proceeding in high Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> though they were of the ſtrongeſt and moſt popular partie, which they the more wondered at, ſince they knew they had but few friends, and themſelues ſmall in number, eſpecially in the beginning of the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:10388:18"/> when there was ſuch ſcarcitie of Civilians, that the Vniverſities tooke little notice of their degrees or profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or the Courts of their practiſe: but now wee haue a moſt happy and hopefull increaſe, and it were to be wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the land were more ſtored with able Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, though they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e not pragmatiques; I meane that the knowledge of the Civill law were more regarded, though the practiſe keepe but the ſame degree of reſpect; for then ſhould wee haue more able Common-wealthes men at home, and more abſolute Statſe-men abroad; for all the nations round about are ruled by the Civill law, as we are by the Common law: onely they haue ſome particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, manifeſtations, and ſanctions, as wee haue ſtatutes and Acts of Parliament; and ſo by that law the treaties we make for matters in queſtion are to bee decided by that law that which is determined by conſultation, and agreed upon, is to bee concluded: ſo that it muſt needs bee, that he that is well ſeene in the Civill law is beſt able to treat with them with more honour and leſſe danger to the ſtate, for in them there is onely the feare and danger of perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, whereas the other may want honeſty and ability both, though their inſtructions bee never ſo punctually accommodated. And this is one maine reaſon (as well as the Popes power) why many Deanes, Biſhops, and Lord Chancellours, who were Doctors of the Civill law were ſent Embaſſadours, when the Nobility had not ſo much law and learning as now they haue; ſo that for this laſt preſent age we haue not loſt ſo much in treating with <hi>France</hi> where the Civill law is moſt practiſed,<note place="margin">Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>11.</hi> li</note> as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme or continue the proverbe which I finde mentioned in <hi>Phil. de Cominaeus; Paectio nulla inter Gallos &amp; Anglos</hi>— in which the <hi>French</hi> did not get the better, <hi>adeoque pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbio dicitur apud Anglos, quoties cum Gallis proelio cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taverint, victores plerunque fuiſſe, quoties verò cum illis pacti ſint detrimentum ſemper aliquid accipiſſe,</hi> which was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:10388:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> moſt verified from the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the 3. to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but it is probable their over-reaching was much helped forward by diſhoneſty, where they found any little want of ability: but grant it were the diſability of our agents, eſpecially in the ignorance of the proceedings and advantages of the Civill law in bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es of tranſ-action wherein the <hi>French</hi> were defendants and paſſiue; yet it was not any honourable advancement to them, though it were ſome ſmall diſadvantage to us: for it is a diſgrace for a Prince to ſtand ſtrictly vpon tearmes, trickes, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of law in the interpretation of treaties; as <hi>Maurice</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> told <hi>Charles</hi> the fift,<note place="margin">Carolus Molinae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lio ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo in cauſa Philip. Lond. graue: Haſſiae.</note> when contrary to agreement, he detained <hi>Philip Landgraue</hi> of <hi>Heſſen; at ego</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>te tanquam Imperatorem, non tanquam iuriſ-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultum &amp; legiſtam, volo pactiones &amp; foedera interpretari.</hi> But ſince treaties are too often ſo interpreted, it is in all probability a great aſſurance of ſafety in treating to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Civill law, at leaſt in the proceedings; and hence it is as I conceiue that in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> it is ſo much eſteemed; ſo that in <hi>France</hi> moſt of the ancient No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility were ſtudents in it, and had amongſt other privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, that they may take the degree of Bachelour at law in three yeares, as it is plaine in the pragmaticall ſanction; which particular is alſo confirmed by the <hi>Concordata Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prag. ſanctio tit. de collatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus. Concordat Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae tit. idem.</note> by <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth; <hi>Bacchalaureo iuris Civilis ſi ex utro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que nobilis, triennium ſatis erit.</hi> In <hi>Italy</hi> alſo it hath beene highly eſteemed, eſpecially in the firſt re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iving of it under <hi>Lotharius ſecundus,</hi> in the yeare 1125: for he found a coppy of the Digeſt and gaue it to the <hi>Piſans,</hi> which was then called <hi>litera Piſana;</hi> but when the <hi>Florentines</hi> tooke <hi>Piſa</hi> (as <hi>Laurence de medicis</hi> told <hi>Politian</hi>) it was tranſlated to <hi>Florence</hi> and made <hi>Pandectae Florentinae;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Angelus Polit. epiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> eſtiſt. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ibi verò in curia loco celeberrimo ſumma religione ſervatur:</hi> and they did not uſe in thoſe dayes in the firſt erecting of their Dukedome, to eſteeme any thing which they found not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:10388:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> beneficiall for the ſtate. But I leaue the commendation of the knowledge of the Civill law to thoſe that know it better, and haue found the helpe of it in long publique practiſing; and betake my ſelfe to my vndertakings, to diſcard ſome exceptions againſt the profeſſours of it, who are Officers practiſing in Eccleſiaſticall affaires.</p>
               <p>They are excepted againſt by ſome that are of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of irregular Proteſtants;<note place="margin">Exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that though the Church of <hi>England</hi> approoue not the <hi>Geneva</hi> diſcipline, yet the principall point is practiſed in it; in theſe our Lay Elders: thus they ſeeke to defame our government by reporting it to bee confuſed and wanting vniformity. But to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and diſcover this groundleſſe exception, the very ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition whereon it is grounded is abſolutely falſe; for though we will not deny that our Eccleſiaſticall Officers be Lay men, yet wee will not grant them to be Elders of the Church: we haue no ſuch Church Burgeſſes, neither doe they take any ſuch Elderſhip vpon them, ſince they know full well that it belongeth only to ſpirituall perſons; which they confeſſe and profeſſe they are not: as that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Civilian D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Couzins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> high ſion. <hi>cap.</hi> 2</note> wee are no ſpirituall perſons as ſome tearme vs, but Eccleſiaſticall: now in my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there is as much difference betwixt a Spirituall perſon and Eccleſiaſticall, as betwixt <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticus;</hi> the one of which is Canonicall, the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryphall; though he be a Canoniſt, I dare without any ſcruple grant them to bee Lay men, not onely becauſe it takes away the ground of the exception, but alſo becauſe it is not any hinderance to their being Eccleſiaſticall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; for the Cannon law which is very ſtrict in this point admits a threefold diviſion of Eccleſiaſticall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; as <hi>primò, in ſacris; ſecundò, in ſacris &amp; ſacerdotio; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiò, nec in ſacris, nec ſacerdotio, vt monachi &amp; legiſtae eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtici:</hi> and ſuch doe the chiefeſt among them account themſelues, for they are well contented to goe for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:10388:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the high court of Parliament. Yea a moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Chauncellour of late refuſed when his Biſhop would haue choſen him a member of the Convocation houſe, and that becauſe hee held himſelfe a Lay man; and ſo they liue in our particular Pariſhes as other Lay Pariſhioners, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church dues, and are alike ſubject to the juriſdiction of their appointed Paſtours in <hi>foro conſcientiae;</hi> and in thus doing they doe declare their exact knowledge in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non law, and pure practiſe of the Civill: for by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law where <hi>Doctores divini &amp; humani</hi> are oppoſed,<note place="margin">Guymer Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: in prag: ſanction: proae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mio. Briſſonij Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> Doctors of the Civill law, yea &amp; Cannon alſo are counted <hi>humane,</hi> and Lay Doctors: for the Clergy (as <hi>Briſſonius</hi> defines it out of <hi>Suidas</hi>) is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But fully to caſt of this exception, I deny them to bee El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our Church; for Elders here I vnderſtand in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Church government, and in that ſence there are no Elders with vs in our Church but Ordinaries; and our Eccleſiaſticall Officers are not Ordinaries, neither doe they vſurpe any ſuch power; but their modeſties are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times forced to take the title and tune of the title from ſome obnoxious fawning Clergy men, who are more ſordidly ſlaviſh then they would haue them: ſo that though of diſcretion they will not ſay to them as <hi>Tyberius</hi> did to the ſervile ſenate,<note place="margin">Tacitus Annal. lib. <hi>3</hi> Extrav. fol. <hi>22.</hi> tit. execrabilis, §. caeterum. Linwood lib. <hi>1.</hi> de ſequeſtratio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nibus. S. Thom. Smith de repub. Ang. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>O homines ad ſervitutem paratos,</hi> yet they cannot chuſe but thinke ſo, for they know that by the Cannon law there is no Ordinary <hi>Iune</hi> but a Biſhop, <hi>per Ordinarios jure intelligimus Epiſcopos,</hi> neither any by priviledge and cuſtome but a Deane, or an Archdeacon. And they doe as fully underſtand that in this Church there are none but what the Cannon law allowes: as S <hi>Thomas Smith</hi> in his diſcourſe of the Common-wealth of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith, by an Ordinary we underſtand a Biſhop, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an Archdeacon or a Deane, who are ſo by privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; or a long preſcribed cuſtome. Now they are not Archdeacons nor Deanes as I would they were, and many
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:10388:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> of them haue beene heretofore, as <hi>Petrus Bleſenſis</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon of <hi>Bath,</hi> who was Chauncellour of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and Chaplaine to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond: for then this excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and all others would bee of no force. But they are now no ſuch Ordinaries as are Church Elders with us, I will grant them in a large ſence to be Ordinaries,<note place="margin">Cor pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tit. §. Gla</note> (as <hi>Guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus</hi> the pragmatique) <hi>Ordinarios latè volo collatores be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiorum, &amp; patronos Eccleſiaſticos,</hi> (as <hi>Glanvill</hi> calls Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons) <hi>advocatos Eccleſiae,</hi> in ſuch a large ſence it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly extended to theſe Eccleſiaſticall Officers; but Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries properly they are not, and that appeares out of the offices they execute in relation to theſe Ordinaries, for they are their Deputies, Deligates, Vicars, Officialls, or Commiſſaries, which are officers diſtinct and derived from their Ordinaries: of all theſe the Biſhops Vicar hath moſt reaſon to be tearmed an Ordinary, &amp; yet he is none; not onely by the Civill law which makes him a miniſter of his Ordinary, <hi>Vicarius eſt qui ſuo Ordinan ſubminiſtrat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bri ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pra con ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Par tali dict Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpec <hi>1.</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dele <hi>Sir Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and</hi>
                  </note> but alſo by the Cannon law, (as <hi>Prateus) Vicarius &amp; Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narius diſtinguuntur, nam vicarius eſt quaſi ſervus in pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio:</hi> (or as <hi>Suidas</hi> calls him) <hi>à ſubſtitute,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and <hi>Panormitanus, juriſdictio Ordinaria non extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitur per mortem illius qui dat, juriſdictio vicarii eſt ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſa ſuſpenſo Epiſcopo,</hi> and <hi>Durantus</hi> affirmes as much; <hi>Vicarii nequeunt officia ſua exercere Epiſcopis eorum excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municatis,</hi> and therefore they doe well in clayming no ſuch power; as S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Ridly</hi> learnedly diſcovering the originall and reaſon of their practiſe in the Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that Civilians or rather Legiſts who were ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Church Lawyers, or <hi>Eccleſiecdici,</hi> were brought into the Church to direct Biſhops; and the Chauncellours at this day are the very ſame in office with them, being aſſiſtants of the Biſhops in their juriſdiction.<note place="margin">Sir con tion jeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> And S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> in his cautious conſideration of Church go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, agrees with him in the approbation of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:10388:21"/> being attended by his Chauncellour, who ſhould be learned in the Civill law for his better inſtruction in points of formality, in the proceedings and courſes of their Courts: And for the ſame purpoſe ſhould Deanes and Archdeacons haue their Officialls and Commiſſaries to inable them to runne through the multiplicity of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to cut off or ſhorten delayes, which in all buſineſſe, eſpecially Eccleſiaſticall, are tedious and odious: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed none are more able in this caſe to aſſiſt them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce cauſes into order, brevity, and paucity; as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Thomas. Aquin. praefa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to his ſummes.</note> he compiled his ſummes to compoſe and compound controverſies, take up and take away all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions. And therefore I doe not a little wonder at D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cowell</hi> who was a moſt able Civilian, that hee ſhould account Commiſſaries or <hi>Officiales foraneos,</hi> onely vſefull in petty peculiars,<note place="margin">D. Cowel. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> verb. Commiſſary. Duaren. de benef. &amp; officijs Eccleſ.</note> exempt from the juriſdiction of the Archdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, otherwiſe to be ſuperfluous and a needleſſe vexation and oppreſſion to the Countrey: ſurely hee meant it of ſome ſuch ſcandalous Courts as <hi>Duarenus</hi> (another lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Civillian) complaines of. <hi>Auditoria Vicariorum &amp; officialium Epiſcoporum, quaecunque profana tribunalia, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſturis &amp; ſtrophis forenſibus, longè ſuperant:</hi> but let him thinke what hee will, I am ſure wee ſee of what good uſe they are, and yet they are not Lay Elders of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exception </seg>2</label> 
                  <hi>Excep.</hi> 2. Is, that the power of juriſdiction Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, cannot be granted to Civilians, that are meere Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>I could ſoone anſwer this exception, by denying them to be meere Lay men, and ſo I would, if I had no other way to avoyd it. But I am willing to giue them ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not to cavill, and therefore will anſwer punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: and that I may ſo doe, and they ſo apprehend it, let them but conſider with me a two-fold power of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Iuriſdiction,<note place="margin">Linwood. lib. <hi>5.</hi> tit. ne praelati vicar. verb. ad firmam.</note> Ordinary, and Delegate; the later and leſſer of which, may be lawfully granted to them;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:10388:21"/> eſpecially, if wee admit the differences and degrees of their commiſſion, which are approved and practiſed in our Church government; both in relation to the power that grants them, and in reſpect to the extent of the grant. Firſt for the power granting them, they are all origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally derived from the Crowne; but ſome haue their power more immediately, as the high Commiſſion haue it vnder the broad Seale: others receiue it more medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, from their Biſhops, Deanes or Arch-Deacons: ſo for the largeneſſe of the Commiſſion, which is <hi>ad v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſitatem cauſarum tanquam Ordinarius,</hi> as the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of high Commiſſion (and not without good reaſon, ſince no cauſe is to be there determined, at leaſt not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced, without the conſent of foure of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> which muſt be, as I am informed, Biſhops:) There is alſo a ſpeciall Commiſſion of Oyer and Terminer, in ſome particular cauſes; and laſtly, a Commiſſion, which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law, is <hi>reſtricta ad inſtantia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Linwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tit. de verb. of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alis.</note> which <hi>Linwood</hi> Officiall of <hi>Canterbury</hi> ſaith, doth belong <hi>officialibus prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalibus,</hi> which wee call Chancellours: Yet I doe not beleeue (by his leaue) that they are ſo reſtrayned, as to a bare cognition, without a definitiue ſentence, though the phraſe, that is vſed to expreſſe buſines of inſtance, be, matters of Eccleſiaſticall cognizance; for, <hi>Cognitio non eſt juriſdictio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cujaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> orig. Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> §. Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> eſpecially now ſince the Lawes haue orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if they be not in ſacred orders, they muſt be aſſiſted by a ſurrogate, who is a Miniſter, and hee is to pronounce ſentence as principall Iudge; which practice hath made ſome of opinion, that anciently they were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant to the ſurrogate, as aſſeſſours; which ſeemes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, becauſe the exact knowledge of the Law is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from an aſſeſſour, not from the principall Iudge (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the moſt conſcionable Caſuiſts:) <hi>Ignorantia juris non eſt peccatum in judice, ſed eſt in aſſeſſore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Navar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iudicis.</note> as the Maſters of the Chancery, who are aſſeſſours to the Lord
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:10388:22"/> Chancellour or Keeper, there is required exact know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, though not in the ſuperiour Iudge, as in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors of the Praetor amongſt the <hi>Romans:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cuj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cius obſer. lib. <hi>23.</hi> c. <hi>40.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Si Praetor per imperitiam iuris iniquum ius ſtatuerit, non punitur; aſſeſſor eius punitur, quia adſeſſor ſe pro iuriſperito agit.:</hi> So that though this opinion be not true, becauſe ſurrogates are not of ſuch antiquity; yet I perſwade my ſelfe without any doubt, that they were, and ſtill are <hi>tanquam aſsiſtentes aſſeſſores Epiſcopis &amp; Archidiaconis;</hi> though they haue alſo a delegated power. And this kinde and degree of Eccleſiaſticall power may be granted to them, though they be meere Laymen; and I beleeue our Church would not haue diſliked the <hi>Geneva</hi> government ſo much, if they would haue choſen ſuch for their Lay-Seigniours, as had knowledge in the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes; as if Doctor <hi>Hottoman,</hi> profeſſour there, and Reader of the Civill Law, had beene joyned with reverend <hi>Beza,</hi> then Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity Reader.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Exception </seg>3</label> Another Exception of like nature and moment, ariſing from the former, is, That vnder the colour of a delegated juriſdiction, they take vpon them Epiſcopall juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and performe all the offices of a Biſhop, in relation to Eccleſiaſticall government.</p>
               <p>This Exception is not peremptory, but dilatory and declinatory, full of impertinent ſurpluſſage, vrging no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or that which is falſe; for no man will vndertake to anſwer what they doe, but what they ſhould doe: <hi>iure noſtro Eccleſiaſtico,</hi> I am ſure <hi>iure noſtro Canonico An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicano,</hi> publickly knowne, and by the old Canon Law which may here be practiſed, (where it is not contrary to the Lawes of the Land) they are not to exerciſe any ſuch power,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>25.</hi> Hen. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Summa bullarij in Pio <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> as doth perſonally belong to a Biſhop, either as he is Dioeceſane, or as he is Ordinary, <hi>in puris ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> neither doe I finde, that ever any Vicar did vſurpe or deſire any ſuch power, but onely Cardinall <hi>Wolſie,</hi> who
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:10388:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> deſired <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh <hi>ſuo vicario vniverſale in Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>terra, &amp; in Germania, mentre ſtava in prigione,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Guic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. hiſt. li</note> his Vicar generall in <hi>France, England</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his impriſonment; which he could not doe by Law, being his Ordinary and ſuſpended, if not <hi>ab officio,</hi> yet <hi>á beneficio:</hi> and if it had beene lawfull, yet the Pope had betrayed his weakneſſe much to grant it, with that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, during the time of his impriſonment; for the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall would without doubt haue endeavoured to keepe him there ſtill, to continue his vicarſhip. And moreover this, I finde that by the Canon Law, <hi>ſede vacante,</hi> the Deane or Chapter is ſucceſſour, or rather adminiſtratour to the Biſhops in their juriſdiction, and guardian of the ſpiritualties; and no marvell, for they are called <hi>fratres Epiſcopi, Cardinales Papae;</hi> they can diſpence <hi>in cauſis Epiſcopo reſervatis,</hi> and call Convocations,<note place="margin">Laeliu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us de p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> capitu</note> to which the Biſhops Vicar may not be admitted; <hi>&amp; poſſunt condere &amp; revocare ſtatuta.</hi> And during the life of the Biſhop, the Arch-deacon is his Vicar <hi>iure</hi> (as <hi>Zerola) vicarius natus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zerola Epiſc. Archi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> (as <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi>) which they vnderſtand in reſpect of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction <hi>in ſpiritualibus;</hi> for not they, but the <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presbyter</hi> is Vicar <hi>in divinis,</hi> which is, <hi>in ſpiritualibus,</hi> in relation to the power of order: So that you ſee, they take not any ſuch ordinary power vpon them, but leaue it to the Biſhops, and their moſt naturall and lawfull Vicars in that power;<note place="margin">Form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tattor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>enſis.</note> and yet they may be their Vicars <hi>in Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificalibus</hi> (as the Canoniſts expreſſe it) which is, in thoſe cauſes that belong to their Sees, as they haue pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and prerogatiue Courts; and ſuch may be Lay-men according to the moſt moderate moderne Decretiſts; <hi>Syndicos</hi> (ſaith <hi>Duarenus) ſiue defenſores,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Duar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> officijs l. <hi>1.</hi> c.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; apocriſiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ſiue reſponſales laicos poſſe eſſe;</hi> though by the old Canon Law <hi>Vicarius Epiſcopi debet eſſe Clericus.</hi> And it is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one of the inſolent rare actions of the Popes, <hi>cauſas Eccleſiaſticas Laicis delegare:</hi> This juriſdiction they may
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:10388:23"/> haue without any trenching vpon the office of a Biſhop in his perſonall juriſdiction, which I conceiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nnot be delegated to a lay perſon;<note place="margin">Durand. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. Iuriſ. Eccl. Con. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> being that juriſdiction, whereby he doth exerciſe and execute his correctiue, coercitiue, coactiue power, which is the inſtrument of his paſtorall paternall care over his Clergie, and proceeds from the power of conſecrated order, and is inſeparably vnited to it: which power, I finde fully, yet briefly expreſſed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Cyprian,</hi> ſpeaking of a contumacious Deacon to his Biſhop;<note place="margin">Cypr. Epist. Rogat. Epiſc.</note> he adviſeth the Biſhop, <hi>vigore Epiſcopalis cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drae aut deponas eum aut abſtineas,</hi> either to degrade or ſuſpend him; neither of theſe will a Lay delegate doe; yet I grant he may ſuſpend, if not <hi>ab officio,</hi> yet <hi>à beneficio.</hi> And for their viſitations, which are an act of ordinary juriſdiction, they performe them not <hi>ex officio,</hi> but by a ſpeciall commiſſion. And for the forme and force of their inquiſition in them, it is not generall concerning the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and manners of the Clergie, but directed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained according to the Biſhops Articles,<note place="margin">Formula viſit. Dioeceſis Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſis.</note> and without requiring an oath of the party preſented; <hi>viſitatores inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogabunt abſque exactione iuramenti;</hi> yet I doe not diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue that an oath ſhould be required vpon a fame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it reſpects as much the purgation, as the conviction of the jurant.</p>
               <p>And for the ſentence of excommunication, which ſome make the proceſſe of ſpirituall Courts, in point of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy; I am not able, I confeſſe, fully to ſatisfie in that point, but I dare ſubſcribe to what iudicious Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſaith of it, to cleare it; who, I am ſure, could and would ſay as much in the behalfe of Eccleſiaſticall officers as any Biſhop of his time, who ſpeaking of the power of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,<note place="margin">De perpetua guber. Eccl. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith, <hi>Nequaquam ſibi clavium poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem aſſumunt, ſed poenam ob contumaciam infligunt, quâ omnes illae animadverſiones continentur, quae legibus in eos ſancitae ſunt, qui claves Eccleſiae temerè contemnunt, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:10388:23"/> nomine appelletur, ſive ſuſpenſio, ſive condemnatio, aut excommunicatio nil refert, dummodo ne poteſtatem hanc divino, ſed humano iure ſibi vendicent, nil cauſae tunc eſt, quin Iudices civiles delinquentem in poenam Canonis inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſe declarent.</hi> But the maine ground of theſe, and ſuch like exceptions, is, becauſe Civilians are not in orders with vs, as moſt Canoniſts be beyond the Seas, (though they haue no title, and are but <hi>Presbyteri Vtopiani,</hi> as <hi>Duare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> cals ſuch) if then our Eccleſiaſticall officers were all in orders, as ſome of them are, then they could not with any reaſon except againſt them for Lay-men, no more then they can againſt the Pontificiall Canoniſts, who haue farre more Eccleſiaſticall power, eſpecially the moderne Legiſts, and are as able to judge of hereſie, as the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> vnder <hi>Zachary,</hi> who condemned <hi>Virgilius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Saltzburge</hi> of hereſie, becauſe he affirmed,<note place="margin">Aventi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nal. lib.</note> that there were <hi>Antipodes;</hi> when as <hi>Iſidorus Hiſpalenſis</hi> was not condemned for holding hell to be at the <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tho. Aq ſuppl. qu Art. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> neere three hundred yeares before. Yet theſe are the only men that are now judges of hereſie, which makes modeſt <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> complaine,<note place="margin">Melchio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib. <hi>8.</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non video quonam conſilio in cognitione haereſeos, partes poſtremae, ne dicam nullae theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logis permittantur; juriſconſultis verò vel primae, vel etiam omnes.</hi> When as with vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
                  </note> not our Chancellours nor Commiſſaries, nor our Biſhops alone may determine of hereſie: and yet I beleeue any of them haue as infallible aſſurance of truth, as immediate vocation, commiſſion, aſſiſtance by inſpiration, as all they; but onely they are in orders, ours are not; as the twelue auditors of the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Court of the <hi>Rota</hi> are the Popes Chaplaines by their office, (as <hi>Lelius Zecchius de auditoribus Rotae</hi>) and ſo are thoſe irrefragable referendaries: and the Popes finde great good in having them in orders; for you ſhall not find, but the Canoniſts haue alwayes ſtood for the Popes prerogatiue; but onely <hi>in Concilio Piſano Guic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciardine</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:10388:24"/> ſaith) they that were for the Councell which was called againſt <hi>Iulius ſecundus,</hi> by ſome of <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfthes faction,<note place="margin">Guicc. hiſt. l. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Che de canoniſti autoritata del convocare i Concilii, nelle riſedere ſolamente, perſona del Pontifice.</hi> But it was not ſo much the Canoniſts, as one principall one, which was <hi>Philippus Decius</hi> of <hi>Millaine,</hi> where the Councell began,<note place="margin">Car. Mol. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Decij Conſil. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> who defended the cauſe, as appeares out of <hi>Carolus Molinaeus</hi> his Annotations vpon <hi>Decius</hi> counſels; ſo that the Popes knew what they did, when they ſhewed and granted ſo many favours and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the Vniverſitie of <hi>Bononia;</hi> as <hi>Gregory</hi> the ninth dedicates his Decretals to <hi>Bononia,</hi> ſo <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight his Sext, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the two and twentieth his Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentines, and Extravagants; thus they are formally qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified by orders; and becauſe our Eccleſiaſticall officers are not ſo, ſome take and make theſe exceptions: ſo that I will conclude this briefe Digreſſion, with this wiſh, not altogether voyd of hope: I would more of our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Civilians were Divines,<note place="margin">Abbas Panorm. Lect. in Decr. <hi>120.</hi>
                  </note> or more of our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Divines Civilians, <hi>Cum Theologia &amp; Ius Canonicum fraternizent.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="conclusion">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:10388:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE SECOND CONCLVSION.</hi> That vnder the dominion and protection of this Civill State, this State Eccleſiaſticall is moſt likely to enjoy all thoſe rights that can any way belong vnto it.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough they that ſit at the tops and ſtearnes of States, amongſt all their great and graue cares, doe little regard the opinion or cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure of private men, ſince they are no bound to giue a reaſon of their lawes, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an account of their actions, their admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration being abſolute. Yet if by theſe lawes, privat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perſons deſerue and ſuffer publick puniſhment, not onl for offering private wrongs, but alſo for with-holdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> particular rights: ſurely theſe law-makers and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators of juſtice, that will not ſuffer injuries vnpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will be ſo farre from doing wrong, though it be but to poore and private men, that they will feare, though they cannot flie the ſuſpition of it, and be as carefull to obſerue a juſt and geometricall proportion in the diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of dues and duties. Now if private and common ſubjects are not onely ſecure from injuries, but alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:10388:25"/> to due deſert publickly regarded, and rewarded for their particular ſervice to the common-wealth, though their ayme be but at their owne perſonall and private profit; one may ſafely conjecture, that the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and politick parts and pillars, the diſtinct and ſetled ſocieties of that State ſhall be as ſtrongly ſecured from detriment by wrongs, and as freely and fully favoured by advancement in rights. Yea it may be fully preſumed, where a State is ſo framed, that they are all vnited in one head, without dependance and ſubordination to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As in a Monarchie, which with an equall impartiall proportion, giues protection, diſtributes rewards; when as if their vnion and communion be continued by a colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torall relation, and mutualitie of members, their equality of power and deſert would breed emulation, if not envie and indignation, and make them ingratefull to each other, if they be not injurious.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ariſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> As it is where the government is Ariſtocraticall, which may be ſeene in the envious oſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmes of the <hi>Athenian, Epheſian, Venetian</hi> States: <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides hiſtoricus in exilium pulſus erat, quae fortuna opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo cuique Optimatum Athenis accidere ſolet,</hi> (as <hi>Paulus Iovius</hi> ſaith of the <hi>Venetian</hi> common-wealth.<note place="margin">Cicero de Orat. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>) <hi>Neminem temerè ex Optimatibus qui vel inſigni virtute, vel ſpiritu in gerendis rebus, caeteris antecellat, potentem &amp; clarum fieri patiuntur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iovius Hiſtor. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Machi vel. diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> So that it is but a perverſe and peeviſh para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox in <hi>Machivell,</hi> to hold, that a princely Monarch vſes to be more vngratefull, than free and popular States, when as they either returne malice and miſchiefe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of ſingular merits; or if ſuſpicion, which he makes one ground of ingratitude, doe not make them, at leaſt to ſuſpend them by a relegation; yet avarice, which is his other ground, will make them really ingratefull, though formally they pretend a reward. For if they giue any thing, it will not be worth the taking, <hi>in ſtatu populari &amp; liberis civitatibus, praemia liberalitatis plus habent honoris
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:10388:25"/> quàm vtilitatis;</hi> they beſtow nothing but vaine, vaniſhing,<note place="margin">Bodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> empty, and aërie titles, which are blowne vp, blowne out, and blowne away with the breath and voyce of the vulgar that gaue them, ſo that they doe him that is grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed no right and reall good:<note place="margin">Ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; it is not gratifying to giue things that are contemptible, for no man will confeſſe that hee hath neede of them, but theſe toyiſh titles doe men more harme then their ingratitude could. For titles without proportionable eſtates; doe not onely fall vnder the miſerable ſuccour of other mens pittie, but are alſo a temptation to provoke all men to contemne them. But one maine reaſon of this difference in rewarding is, that Ariſtocracies reſpect themſelues in it, when as a Monarch to whom all giue due and loyall reſpects, doth powerfully protect and royally reward with reſpect to all. But as all our moderne Monarchies are diſtinguiſhed into ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as in ſome Kingdomes there are fiue States;<note place="margin">Theſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apotel</note> as in <hi>Denmarke, France,</hi> and in <hi>Brittaine</hi> three, which as they are ſubordinate and inferiour one to another, ſo the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Governour doth regard and reſpect them with different degrees of favour and care, with conſideration of what conſequence they are to him, and ſo proportions penſions, and of what need they ſtand of him; and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords protection, ſearching into the ſeverall circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their imployments and abilities, as of what vſe they are in point of neceſſitie, vtilitie, and honour. Now all theſe three States are neceſſary, profitable, and for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Prince, but not equally at any time, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly at all times; neither in reſpect of peace or warre, domeſtique or forraine: ſo that as one ſtate doth make it ſelfe more neceſſary in relation to an extraordinary time of neede, ſo another may be more profitable in the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſupplying of ordinary expences: and the third may bee more for the honour of a King, both in ordinary and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:10388:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> extraordinary actions. Now a King that preferres his honour before his profit, at all times will more reſpect that ſtate which ſtands ſtrongeſt for his honour at all times, then that which is more profitable at all times; ſo will hee more eſteeme that which certainely ſupplies his ordinary continuall charges, then that which may bee more neceſſary, <hi>ſi coelum ruat,</hi> vpon an extraordinary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for occaſion: becauſe wiſedome is not imployed in preventing, and providing againſt what may be in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, but againſt what is likely in probabilitie: ſo that in the naturall body though there bee more continuall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe and mutuation of needfull ſupplies reciprocally betwixt the head and the heart, eſpecially from the heart: yet thoſe externall members that are neareſt vnited to the head, haue more externall honour, as the eyes, the eares: ſo in the body politique, there is a conſtant interchange of ſuccours and ſupplies betweene the ſtate Civill and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall,<note place="margin">His Majeſties inſtructions to the Biſhops. 1626.</note> yet the ſtate of the Nobilitie eſpecially taken for the Councell, is of higheſt aſſiſtance, which are as it were the eyes and eares of the King in publique provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and intelligence,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Zetzes Hiſtor. Clibias. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> (as <hi>Dion Chryſoſtomus</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Theſe principall Peeres that are ſo cloſely vnited to the head, that they communicate with it in the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and ſerious adviſings, deſervedly enjoy the faireſt fortunes and favours; for it is great reaſon that Kings ſhould heape and beſtow vpon the watch-towers of the ſtate the greateſt and higheſt honours in the ſtate: that as they are neareſt, ſo they may be deareſt, being his right truſty and well beloved Councellours. And their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment is no more immediately eminent then the truſt of it troubleſome and dangerous.</p>
            <p n="2">§ 2 And the next ſtate in high eſtimation with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Protentates, and with many the moſt eſteemed in all reſpects is their Clergie, the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall; vpon
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:10388:26"/> which they haue heaped favours to the very exhauſting of their treaſures.<note place="margin">Tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Imperium amore religionis ſemetipſum exhauſiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> I am not able to reach the reaſon in point of ſtate, of that extraordinary extravagant large liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but thus much I am able to compaſſe and conceiue, and ſhall endeavour to make it plaine; that whatſoeuer right and reaſon any King in <hi>Europe</hi> hath had for this 400 yeares to vphold his Clergie, and conferre favours and honours vpon it; our preſent ſupreame head of our Civill ſtate hath all that right, and more reaſon to bee as royally indulgent to our preſent ſtate Eccleſiaſticall, as none can deny: but as he that hath chiefty of power over the whole body of the Common-wealth, may rightly and juſtly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, beſtow rewards, priviledges and power vpon any publique ſocietie, or private perſon in the ſame: ſo none will affirme that all that haue ſupreame power haue the ſame equalitie of right, to endow with priviledges, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich with rewards; becauſe that all doe grant that all Kings haue not Dominion in the ſame equall altitude and latitude, and ſo cannot ſo highly advance in priviledges, leaſt they ſurmount their petty prerogatiue: nor ſo largely giue them power and revenewes, leſt their extention ſhorten their owne. And the grounds of this inequalitie are diverſe, in handling of which I will neither follow <hi>Machivell,</hi> nor <hi>Iunius Brutus;</hi> becauſe I finde them to runne into two extreames, the one granting it to all out of the looſeneſſe of a wanton wit; the other denying it to all, being carried by the ſtream of innumerous particular au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities; &amp; that becauſe, as the other wanted conſcience, ſo he wanted experience: or rather becauſe <hi>Machivell</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when all Princes in <hi>Italie</hi> claimed and vſurped equall and full power, and ſo writ what they did, not what they ſhould doe; and <hi>Brutus</hi> might endeavour to diminiſh the power of all, becauſe he would not haue the <hi>French</hi> King haue ſo much, which he might thinke too much for the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:10388:27"/> preſent: if hee conſidered it with the times before <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh, wherein as the Peeres and Parliaments had too much, ſo the Kings had too little: ſo that their diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Dominion is not according to that fullneſſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can make it when they are once in poſſeſſion of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; nor according to that diminution wherewith diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall ſubjects impaire it, when they threaten and raiſe a rebellion; but it is according to the ſeverall meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they attaine or obtaine their Kingdome. Now all ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Dominion in a Monarchie is attained by conqueſt or ſucceſſion, or obtained by election: Kings that come to it by the right of conqueſt may haue as much power as they will take; they make their owne Charters: thoſe that come to it by ſucceſſion haue as much power as their anceſtours, accepting of ſuch lawes as they finde; thoſe that haue it by bequeſt,<note place="margin">Cujacius obſerv. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and are adopted heires (for adoption is good by laſt will and teſtament) haue the ſame right that a naturall ſucceſſour hath, if the adoption ſtand good.<note place="margin">Hottoman. il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtr. quaeſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> As the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> was giuen to <hi>Edward</hi> the third by <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixt: but thoſe that are called to it onely by election, their power is reſtrained and curbed with cautionary conditions, and ſtands limited by them.</p>
            <p>Now if all theſe haue great power in their ſupreame government, by any one of theſe rights to attaine a Kingdome; ſurely hee that hath it by all theſe rights con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, hath more power then any hath that is intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to it but by one,<note place="margin">Briſſonius de Regno Perſico. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> eſpecially by election. But our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent gratious Soveraigne hath it by lineall ſucceſſion from an abſolute Conquerour, which was confirmed to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of pious memory, by the Nuncupatiue will of his ſacred predeceſſor,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno Iacobi:</hi> A juſt recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> who then adopted him, and all was made ſure vnto him by the electiue aſſent of the ſupreame Nobility, without any croſſe-courſe conditions, (as falls out) when the ſouldiers or people elect. And as it is
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:10388:27"/> plaine that hee holds by all theſe, ſo I doe conceiue I could make it appeare, that moſt Kings in Chriſtendome hold primarily and principally but by one of theſe, and that of leaſt power. But that I am loath to touch the tickliſh and tender titles of forraine Potentates; neither will I ſpeake any thing of them as their ſtates now ſtand, but onely in a word ſhew what anciently they were: for in my poore judgement their government may bee as good and lawfull, if they haue had the power and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to caſt off and free themſelues from theſe bridles and curbes of government: for not the moſt limited pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but the beſt rectified is ſafeſt both for Prince and people.</p>
            <p n="3">§ 3 To ſhew then how it was with them heretofore, and to begin with the Empire after it was tranſlated to the <hi>Almaine.</hi> Long hath that Empire continued by the election of the high Chamber of the <hi>Septem-viri,</hi> the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſelected Electors of <hi>Germany;</hi> and ſome of the beſt Emperours haue ſo well liked it, that they haue not onely beene willing to take the promiſſarie oath containing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſtrict conditions, but haue alſo granted them new free Charters; and large prerogatiues; as <hi>Charles</hi> the 4. in his <hi>Bulla aurea,</hi> and ſo held ſo looſe and light a hand over them, that one of the Electors, the Biſhop of <hi>Ments,</hi> in the Councell at <hi>Franckford,</hi> ſaid, the government was Ariſtocraticall, which might bee well taken if he meant it with reference to the Councell.<note place="margin">Clap Arca lib. <hi>5</hi> Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>10.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cia l. man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Guic hiſt. <hi>Iere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> The Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> ſeemes not to haue beene anciently ſo abſolute and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained as now it is, for the twelue Peeres of <hi>France, qui ſunt ut in Germania principes electores,</hi> had not onely roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all priviledges, and did not owe ſimple ſubjection, but reſpectiue homage; and had a regall authority in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Provinces, and the command of the chiefe forces: but alſo had the power, if not to elect their King, (as <hi>Nauclerus</hi> ſaith) and as it ſeemes true, becauſe they haue
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:10388:28"/> depoſed them; yet to determine, when there is no great doubt who ſhall ſucceed: and their ſetting alwayes vpon an heire male (which is the courſe of electiue ſtate) ſhewes it to bee ſomewhat electiue; for the reſtraining of it to the heire male, did not primarily proceed from the Salique law, becauſe many of their Kings haue beene <hi>Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raines;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hottoman. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollogia Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica. <hi>§. 6.</hi>
               </note> which Dukes, (the <hi>French</hi> Civilians ſay) doe not obſerue, nor are vnder the Salique law: but if it bee not electiue, it ſeemes not to be ſo cleare a ſucceſſion, becauſe it is a maſculine feud entayled vpon the heire male: yea the predominant extravigant power of the <hi>Pariſian</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſeemes to intimate, that the ancient ſtate was not ſo free and abſolute a Monarchie; for they called in the Kings edicts, ſent forth the contrary: and no appeale lay from their ſentence. <hi>Contra illud tantum ſupplicare licet,</hi> a petition of right onely was permitted;<note place="margin">Gymerus Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. in prag. ſanct. tit. de autoritate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliorum.</note> ſo that this ſtate which is moſt abſolute of all others, ſeeemes to haue been anciently not ſo free and uncontroleable in its govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a free Monarchie ought to be. The next is the Kingdome of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which hath of old beene ſo diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the continuall incurſions and invaſions of the <hi>Moores</hi> and <hi>Saracens</hi> from the South, and <hi>Gothes</hi> from the North, that it hath ſcarce time to ſettle, as water toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But when it did pitch vpon the forme of a Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, it was electiue, as appeares out of the Councell of <hi>Tolledo;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il. Toletan. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Si quis ad Regiae Majeſtatis pervenire faſtigia am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit abſque electione nobilitatis Anathema ſit:</hi> yea and in their latter dayes their forme of inauguration, doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and imply the ſame: for thus it runnes, <hi>Nos qui vale mos, tanto comme vos, y podemos mas quae vos, vos ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemos.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieronymus de Blanca de Hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egamine.</note> 
               <hi>Rey, con eſtas, y eſtas conditiones, intra vos, y nos:</hi> yea and the Juſtice of <hi>Aragon</hi> hath had as much power as ever the Parliament of <hi>Paris;</hi> as in plaine, not onely in their vnlimited immunities, but alſo the power they vſed againſt the Kings edicts: as may bee ſeene in their writs,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:10388:28"/> called <hi>los manifeſtados, y iure firmos;</hi> from which power,<note place="margin">Idem Thua</note> though the Inquiſition haue freed the Kings ſince <hi>Fardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nando:</hi> yet I doe not conceiue how that ſtate ſhould bee more free then before, becauſe it is vnder the power of a tyrannicall Inquiſition. So that the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> had done more providently in preventing their prevailing greatneſſe, if wee conſider their domeſtique freedome in government; though their advancement may advantage them to bring forraine ſtates vnder their ſervitude. But it was hard to hinder them from at leaſt ſo much power as they were able to take from the other, ſo that <hi>Tullie</hi> had no great reaſon to aske <hi>Atticus,</hi> (and that in Greeke as a ſecret,<note place="margin">Ad A <hi>9.</hi> ep</note> not to bee vnderſtood of any that ſhould inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept his letters) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, few doubt it, and this may bee moſt vnqueſtionable with <hi>Spaine,</hi> witneſſe <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Millaine.</hi> Theſe Inqiuſitors are like Ephori in the <hi>Spartaine</hi> republique, whoſe Kings are obſerved to haue the moſt reſtrained power:<note place="margin">Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for the chiefe of theſe Inquiſitors hath a great power over the King in his owne Court. <hi>Inquiſitor generalis, qui Aulam Regiam ſequitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ lit.</note> 
               <hi>cum adjunctis conciliarijs Eccleſiaſtici or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis poteſtatem contra ipſum Regem vſurpari poteſt:</hi> ſo that by all this it is plaine, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarchie hath not long beene a free Monarchie at home. But that which makes moſt, to proue theſe ſtates not abſolute, is becauſe an appeale will lie from any of them to the Optimates and orders of their Kingdomes, for <hi>extrema provocatio</hi> is one principle; <hi>inter ſumma iura imperii:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clap Arc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib.</note> 
               <hi>In imperio tamen Germanico, (vt teſtantur pragmatici) ad ſacram &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Cameram provocatur, apud Gallos ad octo curias mato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, apud Hiſpanos ad quatuor curias;</hi> even as a generall Councell is aboue the Pope being electiue. As for the other ſtates of European Monarchies, without all queſtion they are at this preſent electiue; as <hi>Poland</hi> which made their King <hi>Mieciſlaus</hi> ſend <hi>Lampartus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Craco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:10388:29"/> to Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the ſeaventh, <hi>vt Regem ſe Polonorum &amp; poſteros ſuos eſſe iuberet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Herbert. hiſtor. Poloniae lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed ea res propter iuſtas cauſas, ad aliquod tempus dilata fuit:</hi> yea, it was never obtained, but it ſtill continues electiue; <hi>Moderata eſt principis Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae poteſtas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thuaenus hiſt. lib. <hi>50<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quia non naturae legibus in paternum regnum ſuccedit, ſed communibus ſuffragiis ſenatorii &amp; equeſtris ordinis &amp; publica exclamatione nobilitatis eligitur. Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> alſo is electiue, although the <hi>Spaniard</hi> hath intailed it upon the match with the <hi>Infanta,</hi> which will eaſily bee cut off, and ſuffer a recovery into the former freedome. <hi>In Hungaria liberam habent electionem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cominaeus lib. <hi>10.</hi> Coment.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; inde ab eius morte proceri Budae conveniunt:</hi> I might ſhew the like of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> but no more of that, I know not how this may be taken; but I hope well, becauſe in this I deliver onely what is licenced intelligence, even as <hi>Honorius</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius</hi> did interdict, <hi>ne alicuius regni arcana ſcrutaren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guiccardino Hypomneſes Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lit. <hi>106.</hi>
               </note> but it was with this Proviſo: <hi>Legatus tamen reverſus omnia narrare debet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">§ 4 Theſe inſtances are ſufficient to proue that our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Prince hath moſt vnreſiſtible power, and ſo moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrained right to favour, and freely beſtow immunities, priviledges, and revenewes vpon any ſingle ſociety, or ſingular perſon within his Dominions. Now the next thing to bee prooved is, that as hee hath more right to ſhew favour to what ſtate hee will; ſo hee hath more reaſon then they all to favour his Clergie moſt. This government of our King is not more free in it ſelfe then it is freely and willingly ſuſtained; which ſhewes that it is the ancient equall, and as it were the moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall government of this Iland, and therefore the power is moſt right; becauſe naturallized by cuſtome when as in other Kingdomes, yea in many pettie particular ſtates; that little power they haue improoved by force, they keepe and exerciſe by the ſame meanes. Hence it is that they dare onely truſt forrainers to be their guards: as the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:10388:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>French</hi> haue the <hi>Scots,</hi> and <hi>Suitzers;</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> the low Dutch, which choyſe doth either proceed from tyranny in the Kings, or perfidiouſnes in the nation, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as for inſtance,<note place="margin">Ariſt. R <hi>1.</hi> cap.</note> the firſt Dukes of <hi>Florence</hi> were eſteemed no leſſe, for it was libell-wiſe written over the doore of <hi>Coſmus, De Medices</hi> (the firſt Duke) where he was ſicke, and tooke phyſick, <hi>qui Medicè vivit, miſerè vivit,</hi> which they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the <hi>Medicean</hi> tyrannie, both in reſpect of his feares, and their wrongs in his oppreſſion. And in this age there were ſome, that would haue brought an <hi>Italian</hi> guard into <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> but it was when they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to vſurpe them both;<note place="margin">Thuan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Guiſiani Italorum cuſtodias quòd aſſuetis negotiis ſuis, non ſatis fiderent, adhibent, ſui potiùs quàm regni, aut regis munimento;</hi> when as our Kings haue found out by long experience that to be true, which <hi>Dion Chryſoſtome</hi> told <hi>Trajane</hi> the Emperour,<note place="margin">Dion Ch <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo that they regard no guard, but the loue of the ſubject. But to returne: It is no ſmall encouragement to me, before I argue it in any point, and a ſtrong argument for me, that a ſacred Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne hath and doth proue it true, in his moſt royall and religious practice. For I doe not beleeue, that there hath beene any Emperour, Monarch, or Potentate ſince <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt and the great, that did ever ſo truly and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favour, and carefully protect a poore Clergie as hee hath done. But let vs conſider what great reaſon of this favour there is: wherein I will not ſearch vainly into his Majeſties particular reaſons, for I ſhould not be able to finde them out, becauſe a Kings heart is not to be ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſearched by a private head, that is not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the heigth of their ends: but I will diſcourſe of it a hee is our King; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f from a ſingle relation, there doe ariſe as ſingular reſpect, ſurely a double portion of reſpect will follow a double relation. Now this Ariſtocraticall Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:10388:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> haue not onely relation to their Prince, as hee is a crowned King and they his lawfull ſubjects, but alſo as hee is the Lords annoynted, defender of the faith, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his juſt title (as his Maieſtie pleaſes to ſpeake in his declaration before the Articles.) For they alſo are the Lords annoynted, deliuering that faith; and the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> of them, the immediate inſtrument of his conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo that as by the crowning, they are by right his ſubiects, ſo this annoynting of God, ſuperinduceth a brotherhood betwixt Kings and Biſhops (as S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> in his Booke to King <hi>Iames</hi>) for this relation is onely ancient in our Kings amongſt the Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome; for though, as our Soveraigne is crowned by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> ſo the Emperours when they were Kings of <hi>France,</hi> began to be annoynted and crowned by the Archbiſhops of <hi>Mentz, Collen,</hi> and <hi>Trier,</hi> as they were Emperours; and by the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> as they were Kings of <hi>France.</hi> Yet the Kings of <hi>France</hi> of the firſt line, at leaſt, were not annoynted (as one of the freeſt Hiſtorians confeſſes) <hi>De la primiere Lignèe oinct ny ſacre à Rhemes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Girarddu Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon des affo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And though the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> are crowned by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Tolledo,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Denmarke</hi> by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Vpſale,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Polonia</hi> by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Gueſire,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Hungarie</hi> by the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Strigon,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Navarre</hi> by the Biſhop of <hi>Pampolune,</hi> yet none of them were anciently annoynted. Now it cannot be denied, but as this reall relation doth more peculiar and appropriate the State Eccleſiaſtick to our King,<note place="margin">Vid. Legibus ſaucti Edvardi.</note> ſo it makes him not onely the ſupreame head and governour, but alſo the chiefe guide and guardian: for by it he is more than a meere Lay-man; hee is a mixt perſon, having ſupreame Eccleſiaſtick as well as Civill government, <hi>Reges ſancto oleo vncti ſunt ſpiritualis iuriſdictionis capaces.</hi> Which ſentence was applied to our King, in the time of <hi>Edward</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:10388:30"/> the third:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>33.</hi> Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Aide l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gryme <hi>12. §.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Guymer</hi> in his Comment on the pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſanction of <hi>France,</hi> is peremptorie <hi>quòd Reges inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti non ſunt meri Laici;</hi> and addes, <hi>inde Reges Angliae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferunt beneficia.</hi> So that by this is there ſome addition granted to the power of Princes over the Church. Though the old gloſſe vpon the <hi>Clementines</hi> avouch, <hi>quòd vnctio nil addit ad poteſtatem Imperatoris,</hi> which the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorian edition of the Common Law did well to diſlike,<note place="margin">Cleme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tit. <hi>6.</hi> Regis.</note> but they ſhould haue done better, not to haue given a worſe. And if it adde to their power over the Church, then as they haue more right by it, ſo they haue more reaſon from it to doe what good they pleaſe for the Clergie. So that, doe but conſider the quality and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of our Kings perſon, to doe for his Clergie, and you will ſay, he hath greateſt reaſon of any Prince. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider againe the reaſons on the part of the preſent State Eccleſiaſticall, and you ſhall finde, that they deſerue more of their Prince, than any Clergie theſe foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares.</p>
            <p n="5">§. 5. But I muſt preſuppoſe before that will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that our <hi>Monarch</hi> of great <hi>Brittaine</hi> hath not any reaſon to giue or beſtow meanes and revenues vpon any forraine State Eccleſiaſticall. No Prince hath reaſon to beſtow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is free favours vpon any, over whom hee hath (for the preſent) no right to rule, nor hath heretofore promiſed it, neither by himſelfe, or by his predeceſſours, and thereby bound himſeſfe to farther and favour them. So that, though the Romane Clergie doth claime and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour for revenues and priviledges from our King, yet as they haue no right to claime them, ſo they haue no reaſon to expect them: for they are ſo farre from being his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving domeſtick ſubiects, that they are his deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though they be imbred and homebred. They haue not then any right; for neither our K. nor any of his law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full predeceſſours, did ever binde themſelues to any ſuch
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10388:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> performances. Later &amp; better learned writers of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh faction, finding by the carefull and curious examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſundry paſſages in infinite interpreters, how hard a thing it was, to proue their vniverſall ſupremacie <hi>in temporalibus,</hi> by direct evidence out of Gods word, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to proue it by Charter-grant, and priviledge from Princes pieties, as <hi>Auguſtinus Steucus (Librarian</hi> to Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third) ſets downe the claime the Pope laid to all the kingdomes in Chriſtendome, grounding all from the particular grants from the Kings, but eſpecially <hi>Boniface</hi> the eights letter of Demands. As for inſtance, from <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> the firſt and the beſt, one <hi>Phocas</hi> the firſt and the worſt, from the vniverſall gifts of thoſe vniverſall Emperours, they ground a generall right in all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. The <hi>Bononian</hi> Canoniſts deale cunningly, and ſeeme to deale ingenuouſly, playing the ſophiſters more than the ſycophants in this point, diſcourſing of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Constantine;</hi> for they lay it downe as a preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed preſumption in the Law: That there is ſuch a true deed, notwithſtanding there be no mention made of it in any part of the ſincere Civill Law. <hi>Sed quae notabiliter fiunt, ſpecialiter notanda ſunt.</hi> But they never queſtion it <hi>de facto,</hi> but enquire <hi>quo iure,</hi> and, <hi>an ſit revocabile;</hi> and ſince they doe not full affirme, that he gaue it vp <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will not ſo much as ſhew the falſitie of it, but referre all to the moſt judicious and modeſtly moderate amongſt them. But for <hi>Phocas</hi> his grant,<note place="margin">Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>u vias <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. queſt. c. <hi>1</hi> mem. <hi>9.</hi> Decius Conſil. <hi>130.</hi>
               </note> a faithleſſe vſurping tyrant, I leaue it to be judged of, by thoſe that chuſe to meaſure claimes and titles, by the line of equity, and not by the Laſt of ambition. Yet thus I will inferre againſt it, that a Charter granted as this was, chiefly vpon a ground of cunning, with a purpoſe to maintaine a plot, by partie, which was vndertaken and begun by fraud, might haue beene after revoaked by himſelfe, or anulled or repealed by his ſucceſſours. And farther I ſay, that though this
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:10388:31"/> grant were authentick in all points, yet the Popes could haue no right to this kingdome by it, becauſe this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was excluded from the care, protection and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the Romane Empire, neere two hundred yeares before <hi>Phocas.</hi> For <hi>Aelius</hi> L. Lieutenant for <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentimanus</hi> in the parts of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> ſent word to the <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> that they were to looke for no more ayde from the Empire, which was fallen into faction, ſcarce able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it ſelfe, being thus abandoned, all lawes did free them from duty and dependance.<note place="margin">Baron nal. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> But to make theſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall grants the ſtronger, they pretend particular grants from our owne Kings, as from <hi>Ina</hi> King of the Weſt <hi>Saxons,</hi> that was indeed religious, and from King <hi>Iohn,</hi> that was impious, as well <hi>ſans foye,</hi> as his title was <hi>ſans terre</hi> (as the King of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math</hi> 1216.</note> 
               <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond ſaid) <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes nunquam fuit verus Rex;</hi> neither of theſe binde our State; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Peter</hi>-pence contributed to <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Ina,</hi> are called in the lawes of <hi>Conatus, Larga Regis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitas:</hi> and in the abſtract (which is the beſt of the confeſſours and conquerours decrees) <hi>Regis Eleemoſynae,</hi> which imports not due nor duty, but charity, and the Popes to be his beads-man, not the King to be his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mager. There were many manifeſt nullities in King <hi>Iohns</hi> grant, for he had no right to hold the Kingdome, and if he had held it by right, yet he could not grant any thing in prejudice of the whole State, without the conſent <hi>Regni vniverſitatis,</hi> (as <hi>Mathew Paris</hi> tearmeth the Parliament) and a third mullitie is in the force of the grant, where, whatſoever is paſſed in the body of the grant, is reſumed by this <hi>proviſo</hi> in the concluſion,<note place="margin">Math. ibidem</note> 
               <hi>Salvis nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris, Iuſtitiis liberalitatibus &amp; regalibus noſtris:</hi> which being luckily inſerted ſalues all, and makes it abſolutely voyd. But the maine grant which <hi>Baronius</hi> relies vpon, is a donation from <hi>Ethelulphus</hi> King of the Weſt <hi>Saxons</hi> which ſeemes very lawfull, if it were (as he ſaith) <hi>ſalubri
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:10388:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:10388:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:10388:33"/> conſilio Epiſcoporum &amp; Principum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baron. Annal. Anno. <hi>854.</hi>
               </note> but yet that deed (if wee free it from being forged) was voyd, if you doe but conſider amongſt many other things, the incompetencie and incapacitie of the perſon, to whom the deed was made. Now <hi>Baronius</hi> is peremptory, that it was made to the immediate ſucceſſour of <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth, which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all the trueſt writers of the Popes liues, was <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, which they conclude was a woman <hi>fu vna donna natio de Inghilterra che vacata là ſede Apoſtolica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Petro de Mexia della ſilva cap, <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>per la morte di Leon quarto, fu eletta per ſonno Pontifice di Roma</hi> (as <hi>Petro de Mexia</hi>) and <hi>Boccacio de las mugeres illuſtres:</hi> the King might perhaps haue done much for his country woman, if he had knowne it, but ſhee was not capable to receiue ſuch a deed to her vſe, and therefore, the Iuriſts haue reaſon to make this queſtion,<note place="margin">Hottoman. quaeſt. illuſt. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vtrum acta Iohannis octavi in papatu rata eſſe debent:</hi> And if what ſhee did was voyd, what was done for her i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not firme, being it was given, ſuppoſing ſhee was capable. So it is plaine, that this engine is not able to vphold this claime, being ſo looſe, and hanging together in the joynts like ſick mens dreames, ſhewing their inconſiderate inconſtant humours, their proofes being as weake as their imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ſtrong, all ſtanding vpon ſlender ſuppoſals, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular intereſt, making partiall. But they haue another ground for a preſumption of their right, becauſe ſome poore oppreſſed Princes haue deſired to hold their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes from them, as ſome vſurpers ſought to obtaine dominions by their gift, who depoſe Kings, that they may diſpoſe of their kingdomes. But this is nothing, and they ſtand not vpon it, but when they haue nothing elſe to ſay. I doe not by this goe about to deny, that our Kings haue beene bountifull Benefactors to the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergie, but this onely I ſtand vpon, that they haue no reaſon to continue ſo ſtill, ſince they were never lawfully bound to it. Neither doe I deny, that any Prince ſhould conferre fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:10388:33"/> vpon ſome forraine Eccleſiaſticall State with this caution, that he be not prejudiced by the kindnes, &amp; may haue ſo good vſe of their thankefulneſſe: As ſuppoſe any Prince ſhould be called into <hi>Germany,</hi> or <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dies nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tranſit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aliquod p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fecerit, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vt Aera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (vt de Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lampr.</note> or any other kingdom, by an oppreſſed State Eccleſiaſticall, that Prince may doe royally to inveſt them into their former ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all poſſeſſions, and yet never impoveriſh or inſlaue his owne kingdome to them, and alſo binde them to him for protection. Thus did <hi>Pipine, Charles</hi> the great, <hi>Lodovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus pius,</hi> they releeved the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergie, and beſtowed very much vpon them in large territories, but they gaue them nothing in <hi>France,</hi> but onely what they recovered for them in <hi>Italy:</hi> it is then evident,<note place="margin">Guicc li hiſt. Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that our King hath no reaſon to beſtow honour or power, revenues or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges vpon any forraine State Eccleſiaſticall; and it is as plaine, that he hath the greateſt reaſon of any Prince in Chriſtendome to beſtow them all vpon his owne do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Clergie.</p>
            <p n="6">§. 6. The Nobility and the Clergie are the prime pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of a Monarchie, and the Communaltie is the ground whereon they ſtand. And this they well know that intend the ruine of it, for they will be ſure to ſtrike at theſe two props, knowing that then it will fall, and the ground and foundation remaine to them to erect a-new; (as <hi>Ball</hi> a Maſſe-Prieſt, Chaplain to <hi>Wat Tyler,</hi> adviſed his chieftane to deſtroy all the Clergie and Nobility; ſo <hi>Garnet</hi> did the Traytors in the powder-plot, (as the Earle of <hi>Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> well obſerveth:) and therefore <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who was ſeldome in an errour about the vphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or inlarging a Monarchie, adviſes his ſonne <hi>Philip</hi> the third, to ſtick faſt to the Clergie, <hi>los Clerigos amigo,</hi> as I haue beene; but yet ſo, as you diſregard not the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, otherwiſe they will hate you, and envie them, and ruine all. Now if the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> haue reaſon ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to favour their Clergie, as to feare, leaſt their kindneſſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:10388:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> to them, ſhould kindle indignation in the Nobility; ſurely our Prince hath more reaſon ſo highly to ſuccour his Clergie, as that it may not be the object of the contempt of the vulgar. For the Clergie of <hi>Spaine</hi> and all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh faction are not ſimply ſubject to them, but deny Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill obedience alwayes to their Prince, where Canonicall obedience commands the contrary, or priviledges aboue it; when as our Clergie, are as true ſubjects as any State, &amp; renounce all obedience to any other Potentate. So that this hearty adherence to his Majeſtie, is one reaſon, yea they beſtow all their labours in Gods ſervice, onely in dominions expect favour from none but his highneſſe; and they are more beneficiall to their King than any Clergie in Chriſtendome to his natiue Prince, or any State in this kingdome to the Crowne. For though the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of other Clergies, as of <hi>Spaine,</hi> be infinitely aboue ours,<note place="margin">Nicholaus Ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de regno Hiſpaniae.</note> as one of their Hiſtorians, <hi>Opes Eccleſiaſticorum paenè aequales ſunt ſecularium vnà cum Regis.</hi> Yet they are not ſo conſtantly beneficiall to the King, but to the Pope: and if the King get any good ſum or ſubſidie out of them, it is either <hi>la cruzada,</hi> or tenths called <hi>el excuſado,</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him by the Popes indulgence; or if he cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Bull of facultie, he muſt get all they giue by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and force (as Cardinall <hi>de Oſſat</hi> in his letter to <hi>Henry</hi> 4.<note place="margin">Oſſatns epiſt. <hi>274.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>France</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Philip</hi> the thirds ſacriledge.) <hi>Rex Hiſpaniae omnem argenteam ſupellectilem Eccleſiarum &amp; Eccleſiaſticorum ſacrilega manu vſurpare tentat:</hi> when as our Clergie, which haue not the tyth of the tenth part of that meanes is not only now and then profitable in ſmall matters. And if <hi>Francis</hi> 1. beleeved that for a great kindnes from Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, in their conference at the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, to haue the tenths of Eccleſiaſticall livings in <hi>France</hi> for one yeare;<note place="margin">Guicc. hiſt. lib. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Guicciardine</hi> in a judicious ſleighting of the favour: <hi>Promes ſe il Pontifice, al re dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gli faculta, di riſcuotere, per vn anno la decima delle cheiſe,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:10388:34"/> del Reame, de Francia</hi> that the King tooke the propoſall into conſideration, and communicated it to his Councell; who thought it a great benefit if he might haue them, <hi>non ſecundum antiquum valorem beneficiorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liae tit. d libus.</note> but as they are improved; ſurely a farre greater benefit it is to haue the tenth every yeare: Subſides moſt yeares, and firſt fruites the firſt yeare, and that not according to the preſent value which is much fallen from the ancient revenewes, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Popes bookes, in moſt, when as Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall preferments are abated halfe in halfe. So that as all other ſtates are more charged, ſo their revenewes are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved accordingly; but the meanes of the Clergie is much impaired, and yet their charges increaſed in many things; in all things keepe the old rate, ſo that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the poverty (as S <hi>Nicholas Bacon</hi> at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell table) we haue no reaſon to exact or expect any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie from the ſpiritualtie, who are ſo exhauſted; yet it is conſtantly the moſt beneficiall ſtate of this Realme to the Crowne, both in ordinary and extraordinary revenewes. In theſe two conſiderations amongſt many, wee ſee they deſerue much, and there is one thing that makes it more ſafe for our King to beſtow greater honour and priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vpon them, then any other Prince; which is, becauſe he hath not the reaſon to ſuſpect them of ambitions aſpiring to a Monarchie, ſince they haue caſt off their Church Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies, as the <hi>Romans</hi> never ſuſpected any of a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall vſurpation, after they had by one conſent caſt out the Kings: ſo that though the Pope ſeeme to favour the Clergy vpon good reaſon, yet our King hath as much, and this reaſon more then the Pope hath, for he hath not onely all the power of juriſdiction the Pope had over them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
               </note> but alſo the revenewes alſo the Pope had from them: and yet is without feare and danger of being rebelled againſt by them, or diſ-throned. But in one thing it is more capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of a royall Potentates bounty and protection, then any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:10388:35"/> forraine Clergie is, in reſpect of its owne Civill ſupreame head, or any ſtate in our owne Kingdome is of our King; and that is, that it is ſo poore and obvious to injuries, that it will make the ordinary bounty of a Prince magnificent, and make his power long, and delight to protect ſuch an innocent ſtate, being neither able to reſiſt, nor ſtrong to endure and ſuffer wrongs: thus from the power of Dominion paſſeth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of protection.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="conclusion">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:10388:35"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE THIRD CONCLVSION.</hi> That all the rights and reſpects that the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall enjoyes or deſires are origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally derived from their relation and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the Civill.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that hath publique power and an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to doe a great good turne for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing a private friend that depends vpon him, will haue much adoe to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to doe it, though the weale publique ſuffer ſome detriment by it. Yet if his friend doe ſo much tender the publique good, that he will not deſire any thing to the prejudice of it; ſurely then the publique perſon out of his engagements and reſpects to the publique good, will leaue off his preſent purpoſe and pleaſure his favorite in ſome things that may doe him good, and the Common-wealth no harme. Even ſo our ſupreame Regent of great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> hath great and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent power, and never wants an opportunitie to doe good, &amp; beſtow favours vpon the well deſerving ſtate of the Clergie; and it were impoſſible for him to hold his royall bountifull hand, if this Clergie ſhould not in all its
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:10388:36"/> petitions; conſider the publique good, apprehending it ſelfe as a member of the Civill ſtate. And hence it is, that though the King hath more power then I beleeue was ever tried, or can be defined, to doe his Clergie good, yet they haue not any thing conferred vpon them; which is not according to the lawes, cuſtomes, and liberties of this Common-wealth. All that the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes, belongs to it as to a principall member of the body politique; and is derived to it from the ſupreame Civill head on which it doth depend, and in whom it is vnited to the Civill ſtate. It is no debaſing or derogation to a ſpiritualitie, to bee thus ſubject to the Dominion of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Soveraigne; for though ſervitude according to the Civilians proceed not from the law of nature, but of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or at leſt from nature corrupted, (as the Schooles) yet orderly ſubjection and ſuperioritie proceed from the inſtinct of pure nature: for in Heaven there is order a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the bleſſed Angels, and in the ſtate of innocency there was ſuperiority, not onely betwixt man and all other creatures, but alſo betwixt man and woman; and had they lived in Paradiſe till there had beene father and ſonne, there ſhould haue beene <hi>Patria poteſtas,</hi> or elſe the fifth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is not morall: and when there had beene many families, there muſt neceſſarily haue beene <hi>Regiae poteſtas,</hi> or elſe the beſt and moſt happy life muſt haue beene without the greateſt happineſſe of life, which is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Now the ſuperiority of our Prince over his Clergie is not an enſlaving tyranny, but a ſweet and a lawfull So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigntie, which government as it is due, ſo it is our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to obey it; for government and obedience are relatiues of equall extent. And as it is no diſparagement to the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall to bee ſubject to our ſupreame Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, ſo it is great benefit to the Clergie, and a ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Laytie, that all the rights and reſpects that they enjoy or deſire, are deriued from that Prince whom both ſo willingly obey.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:10388:36"/>§ 2 All that the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall doth enjoy or claime, may bee reduced to theſe two heads; of power, and of honour: and they deriue theſe from one ſole ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame governour, who is fully qualified by his perſonall eminent authority, to transferre and conferre theſe rights and reſpects to them, and vpon them: for as theſe two the power and honour of the Clergie are inſeparablie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the ſupreame Soveraigne, then in being, and not communicable to any other ſtate: ſo the particular powers and regalities by which they are more eſpecially conveyed; are inſeparably and incommunicably appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to his royall perſon. As for inſtance, the power of the ſtate of the Clergie is originally derived from his Eccleſiaſticall ſupremacie, the honours from his lawes and royall prerogatiue. All Kings I confeſſe haue not Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall government, and that becauſe many giue up their right; ſome know it not, as many of our Kings for many yeares were bereaved of it, in whole, or in ſome principall parts, by giving and granting to the Pope an inch in breadth with them, and he taking an ell in height aboue them. But when the firſt defender of the faith <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth was weary of the weight of that intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable vſurpation, eſpecially when he perceived that the Popes ambition ſoared vpon the wings and winde of the ſpirituall ſupremacie, to a temporall ſuperioritie; The King like <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> that he might fully recover into his power the temporalitie, <hi>poteſtatem Pontificiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iacob origi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> §. 9.</note> 
               <hi>cum Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria potentia coniunxit:</hi> hee reſumed the Eccleſiaſticall power, finding that it was impoſſible in the courſe of the moderne policie of the Popes, to bee ſupreame agent in temporall affaires, while they were the higheſt in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall government; eſpecially ſince theſe powers cannot reſt really divided in a Monarchie, though they bee really diſtinct in a Monarch being a mixt perſon. So that the ſtatutes in the <hi>viceſimo quintò</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:10388:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>primo</hi> of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which determinately ſet downe this power of ſupremacy, are not lawes inductory of a new, but declaratorie of the ancient authoritie of our Prince, with the ſolemne ſignification of their reaſ-ſumption. And our ſacred Soveraigne doth not alone take this power for his right, but many other Potentates in Chriſtendome that haue not ſo much reaſon: As the Kings of <hi>France, Spaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſaurus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit. Apoteleſ. <hi>50.</hi> Guiceiardino hiſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Denmarke, Poland, Hungarie,</hi> and <hi>Sicily:</hi> which three laſt ſtates haue more nearer dependance upon the Pope then any in <hi>Europe;</hi> for <hi>Sicily</hi> hath beene held of him as a ſpirituall feud, as <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Hungarie</hi> were both in one Popes dayes. <hi>Benedict</hi> the ſeaventh converted from Paganiſme,<note place="margin">Herbert. hiſtor. Poloniae lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and one would thinke, and ſo it ſeemes wholly at the Popes diſpoſall, eſpecially in ſpirituall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. Yet in <hi>Sicily</hi> the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> doe not onely claime ſupremacie of over-ſeeing, but alſo ſuperintenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in doing in Eccleſiaſticall employments;<note place="margin">Baron. Anal. Anno <hi>1209.</hi>
               </note> and the Kings of <hi>Poland,</hi> whoſe power is moderated by the limits and conditions of an election;<note place="margin">Thuanus hiſt. lib. <hi>56.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Archiepiſcopos, Epiſcopos coenobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archas dicunt, ſuoque arbitrio eligunt:</hi> and the Kings of <hi>Hungarie</hi> doe vſe the ſame power, and with as much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (in a Canoniſts opinion) as we doe, for though they cannot <hi>de iure,</hi> yet, <hi>Reges Angliae &amp; Hungariae conferunt beneficia &amp; privilegi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Papae.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guymer. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. prag. ſanct. tit. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis.</note> The Kings of <hi>France</hi> haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes beene at defiance with the Pope for this power, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing continually pragmaticall ſanctions in defence of it, eſpecially in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeaventh, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>Carolina ſanctio:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duarenus pro libertate Eccleſ. Gallicanae. <hi>§. 4.</hi>
               </note> which was of that force by vertue of that approbation of the free Councell of <hi>Baſile,</hi> that it curbed and caſheered the Popes power, cauſing them to impeach it by appealing from it almoſt in all cauſes; which <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond perceiving, ſollicited <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh the ſonne of <hi>Charles,</hi> to aboliſh and repeale that ſanction,<note place="margin">Concordat. Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liae Leonina Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</note> being enacted in a ſeditious ſchiſmaticall conventicle, which he well approved for a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:10388:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> when hee was a private Aeneus <hi>Sylvius,</hi> Secretarie to <hi>Fredericke</hi> the third. The King for the preſent called it in, but his wiſdome preſently found the miſchiefe, and rewarded Cardinall <hi>Balve</hi> very well for vrging him to it; as the Popes Legat,<note place="margin">Prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gis ad cil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> apud hiſtor Phili lib. <hi>9</hi> Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Guic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rex Cardinalem Balvam in carcerem detruſit ob detrimentum, conſilio ſuo emergens;</hi> and with ſo much diſpleaſure, that <hi>Philip de Comynes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis Balvenſis carcerem horrendum excogitavit in quem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſus primùm erat &amp; quatuordecem annos detentus, non ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante Pontifice Romano.</hi> The Kings of <hi>France</hi> were ever after ſtout in the defence of that ſanction, till <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt; in his interview with <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, did remit the force of it in the <hi>Concordata Galliae;</hi> which made his ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Secretarie <hi>Budaeus</hi> ſay, <hi>Palladium Galliae proditum eſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Budae lib. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> The Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> in <hi>Caſteile</hi> haue ſome limited ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power, by a late priviledge of <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſixth, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth; but when they ſee their time,<note place="margin">Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> della</note> they take ſo much as ſhall ſerue their turne; as <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond ſeiſed vpon the temporalls of the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Tolledo,</hi> (the Biſhop <hi>Caranza</hi> being apprehended for ſuſpicion of new hereſie) and when <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> ſent to him to vndertake a warre againſt <hi>England,</hi> and told him that he would remit to him all the revenewes that aroſe of that Biſhopricke, <hi>ſede vacante prudentiſſimus princeps re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondet ſe nil de ſuo Pontifici largiri:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> &amp; though at home his power is but what hee pleaſes to take, yet in other of his territories it is lawfully as large as another Princes; as in <hi>Burgundy</hi> and <hi>Belgia</hi> he hath the ſame right the King of <hi>France</hi> once had, as <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth made a ſtatute of <hi>Mortmanie. Nullis perſonis Eccleſiaſticis, vel locis ſacris licet vllam rem immohilem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ lit. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>abſque principis licentia accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, vel habere.</hi> And <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond his ſonne publiſhing the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> in the Low-Countries, did not let it paſſe in all points with the full ſtrength of an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall law, but reſtrained it with an expreſſe clauſe of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:10388:38"/> priviſion, that it ſhould in no wiſe prejudice or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh any priviledge the King enjoyed touching poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary judgements or Eccleſiaſticall livings, or concerning nomination therevnto.<note place="margin">Boter. Heroic. quaſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> But I will not now enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Prince hath ſuch a ſupreame power <hi>iure poſitivo Pontificio;</hi> I am ſure it is <hi>iure divino Apoſtolico:</hi> and ſuppoſing ſuch a power, I will for more diſtinct pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, conſider the ſeverall ſtreames and ſtrings of this Eccleſiaſticall power; and how they flow and are faſtned to the head and top of Soveraigntie, paralleling them in the ſeverall parts and points of this honour, diſcovering how they are annexed to theſe powers, and how they ariſe, are raiſed and ſtand by his Maieſties lawes and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall prerogatiue.</p>
            <p n="5">§ 5 All power Eccleſiaſticall is either power of order, or of juriſdiction,<note place="margin">Durandus de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigine jure Civ. concluſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and both theſe depend vpon the power of ſupremacie. For though theſe powers of order and juriſdiction be immediately derived from Chriſt the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall head of the Church, in reſpect of their inſtitution, commiſſion, internall qualification, and deputation to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to performe them; yet they are mediately derived from our Prince, the miniſteriall head of our particular Church, in relation to their execution. For the power of order cannot bee lawfully exerciſed in theſe dominions, without the licence and permiſſion from the power of juriſdiction; which power is originally derived from the Kings dominion,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Eliz. cap.</hi> 1.</note> over Eccleſiaſticall cauſes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. So that it is plaine in generall, that they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant on his Crowne and ſupremacie: To omit the juriſdiction <hi>in foro conſcientiae,</hi> that depends vpon the power of order, I will for a more particular view of this dependent derivation, conſider the ſeverall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per acts and workes of this Eccleſiaſticall ſupremacie, which (as I conceiue) may be reduced to theſe foure. The firſt worke is reformation of the Church in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:10388:38"/> manners, and ceremonies. The ſecond is convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Councels and Synods, for the reformation. The third is promulgation of the lawes and edicts, proceeding either from his Highnes pleaſure in publick declarations, or the Canons &amp; conſtitutions decreed or confirmed in his Councels. The 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> is, in receiving of appeales, &amp; giving definite, determinate deciſions, reſtitutions, and deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons belonging to cauſes &amp; perſons Eccleſiaſticall. Now all theſe acts haue their effects in the power of juriſdiction; for the reforming power of it, is ordinarily &amp; perpetually derived to Archbiſhops &amp; B. <hi>de iure,</hi> to Arch-deacons and Deanes, <hi>de conſuetudine,</hi> to be executed by them in their Provinciall, Trienniall, and Annuall viſitations: but it is principally reſtrained to the correction of manners. This power is extraordinarily <hi>ad tempus</hi> granted to the Church repreſentatiue in Convocation. It is not turned into a running regencie, rolling round to every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Preſbyter, though it be not an ordinarie ſtanding court, the calling of which is the ſecond worke of ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie. To this Convocation thus called, there is given power and licence, to deliberate of, to order, and doe all ſuch things as ſhall concerne the ſetled continuance of the doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Majeſties royall conſent in the proceeding and determinations (as it is plaine in his Highneſſe declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.) And the lawes they make, take their firſt force from the worke of his promulgation. But before I proceed any farther, I muſt of neceſſity take a little time (though to ſome it may ſeeme an impertinent parentheſis) rejoycing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider the gratious countenance, our pious Prince ſo freely ſhewes to this diſcountenanced, diſabled houſe of Convocation. Little did any thinke, (no not that able abſolute States-man, the laſt Lord-Chancellour, though wiſhed it) that his Majeſtie could haue beene ſo fully and faithfully informed of the ancient power and priviledges
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:10388:39"/> of it, as to thinke of reſtoring them, ſeeing not onely in the opinion of the people, but alſo in the practice of the lower houſe of Parliament it hath beene long diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred from that high Court, and loſt all the power and priviledges as eſcheated to the ſame, inſomuch, that it is queſtioned by ſome, whether ever it was a member of the Parliament or no. But it ſeemes his Majeſtie did ſoone apprehend it to be an eſſentiall part of it, and vpon a ſhort ſearch diſcovered, that though heretofore it was a member, whoſe nerues were wreſted, diſtorted, diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and racked from its naturall head, by extention to a forraine: yet there was no <hi>diſſolutio continui</hi> (as the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians ſpeake) from the head, and therefore not from the collaterall members; and ſeeing it was but a diſcontented diſcontinuance that did cauſe it to be ſuſpected and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, it being now againe contracted and knit moſt firmely to the head, is vnited as cloſely to the members, &amp; may ſafely exerciſe and enjoy all the power and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that did of right belong vnto it, with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for though it was no reaſon, that it ſhould haue the priviledges of the Parliament, when it was diſtracted from it, and aſſembled without it by vertue of the Popes Legates writ, and ſo the power and purpoſe of it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine, and juſtly came within the compaſſe of a <hi>Praemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire,</hi> for the Clergie then was no true member of the common-wealth, and ſo the Convocation cut off from the Parliament; yet when as it is now aſſembled with it by the ſame writ of the King, and the Parliament is not compleate without it, being one of the three Orders, and that State which makes it haue competent power in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Eccleſiaſticall, that it is not a meere temporall Court, and that in the judgement of thoſe that had leaſt reaſon ſo to eſteeme it; for wee finde 1. <hi>Philip. &amp; Mariae, c.</hi> 8.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Phil. &amp; Mar. c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> That the Legate of <hi>Iulius</hi> the third tooke great care to haue Statutes repealed, made againſt the Popes ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:10388:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> wherein hee granted them to be authentically made, and conſequently, that they had Eccleſiaſticall power to enact them, otherwiſe by reaſon of nullitie, they had been cancelled and abrogated in themſelues. And <hi>Antonius de Florebellis,</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> Prelate in his <hi>Panegyrick, de reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta religione in Anglia</hi> ſaith, it is done <hi>honorifico vniverſi Anglorum conſilii decreto,</hi> in which ſpeech,<note place="margin">Florebe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rat. ad Marian</note> he ſuppoſed their power to decree it, which he would not haue done, if hee had held it to be a meere temporall Court; and he muſt neceſſarily haue ſo accounted it, if hee did not reckon the vpper and lower Convocation Houſes, as members of it, exerciſing equall power with equivalent priviledges. As it was plaine in a particular example in that Parliament;<note place="margin">Fox Act pag. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> for when Arch-deacon <hi>Philpot</hi> was queſtioned for ſome words that paſſed from him in the Convocation Houſe, hee pleaded, that hee was privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to ſpeake them, ſince the Convocation was a member of the Parliament; and this plea was not refuſed, but neglected. For they were not ignorant what was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted by <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth, to wit, that all the Clergie,<note place="margin">8 <hi>Hen.</hi>
               </note> which be called to the Convocation by the Kings writ, ſhall fully vſe and enjoy all ſuch liberties, as the great men, and Commons of the Realme haue, that are called to the Parliament. And as they had ſome priviledge, ſo it is plaine by a Statute <hi>viceſimo quarto</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight,<note place="margin">24. <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> (though now abrogated) that they had once as much power in their receiving appeales from inferiour Courts Eccleſiaſticall, when it was a <hi>Praemunire</hi> to appeale to <hi>Rome,</hi> or elſe-where. The words of the Statute, printed in the yeare 1550, are: The partie grieved, may appeale to the ſpirituall Prelates, Abbots, Priors, and Proctors, convocate by the Kings writ, in Convocation. So that the reſtitution of the Convocation, was a worthy conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Majeſtie, ſeeing it is as neerly and deerely annexed to his ſupremacie, as the Parliament is: for his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:10388:40"/> Majeſtie having two capacities of government in him, the one ſpirituall, the other temporall, by both theſe hee hath ſupremacie, and this ſupremacie is chiefly exerciſed in the calling, preſedencie, and diſſolving of the great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the three States, which high Court is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently correſpondent to both thoſe powers in the King, vnleſſe the Parliament conſiſt collectiue of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and temporall perſons, which it hath anciently (if the Booke <hi>De modo tenendi Parliamenti</hi> be authenticall) for hee makes the vpper Houſe conſiſt of three States, the Kings Majeſtie, the Lords ſpirituall and temporall; and lower of the Knights,<note place="margin">Ridleys view of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Lawes.</note> Procurators for the Clergie, and the Burgeſſes; which both anſwer the Kings mixt ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie. So that as he is <hi>ſupremus Iuſtitiarius totius Angliae,</hi> in relation to the temporalitie; ſo he is <hi>ſupremus,</hi> or (as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> truely entitled himſelfe in the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Euſebius in vita. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> in reſpect of the ſpiritualty. But to returne to my preſent promiſe, and purpoſe, which was to ſhew how the actes of ſupremacie haue their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the Eccleſiaſticall juriſdiction, derived to the Clergie: And I am now to ſhew, what effect the power of promulgation of lawes hath, which is in conſenting, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, and publiſhing the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes which are agreed vpon in Convocation (not excluding the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Parliament, becauſe the State Eccleſiaſticall is not an independant ſocietie, but a member of the whole:) hence it is, that they are called the Kings Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Lawes, by which the Clergie is ruled in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall cauſes, according to which they exerciſe their ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction <hi>in foro exteriori &amp; contentioſo;</hi> hence it is, that for this laſt age, the Eccleſiaſticall Lawes of this Realme haue ſo well agreed with the Civill, becauſe they paſſe not without the aſſent of the ſupreame governour. And it were much to be deſired, that Chriſtian Princes would not onely permit lawes to be made, and giue force to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:10388:40"/> them by their authority, but alſo that they would vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe their perſonall preſence, to be Preſidents in all aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies for that end, for then they would proceed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude to better purpoſe. As <hi>Iſidorus Peluſiota</hi> writes to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the younger, to be reſident and preſident in the Councell of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which is, that if hee would be pleaſed to take ſo much time, as to be preſent there, he did not feare, that any thing that ſhould paſſe, could be faultie; but if he leaue it all to be done by turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſuffrages, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>;<note place="margin">Iſiodoru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> luſ. lib. <hi>311.</hi>
               </note> Who can free that Synod from ſcornfull ſcoffings? his counſell was ſafe and ſeaſonable, becauſe the cauſe of feare was very probable and eminent. For in a Councell, where there is a Monarchicall authority, a ſupreame power in one, there will be more diſpatch in deliberations, more expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in executions, than where multitudes of equals ſit alone, for they will be many of them over-wiſe, and moſt over-wilfull to agree in one poynt; when as every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular perſon will broach his particular project, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it as a publick law, with reſolution to be a recuſant to all their lawes, if they will not be Proteſtants to his: and ſo it comes to paſſe too often, that they are forced to yeeld to one another, or elſe no law ſhould paſſe. Hence is that multiplicitie, vncertainty, confuſion &amp; contrariety of lawes in ſome diſeaſed States, than which nothing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers a State to be more deſperately declining, though they are good in their particulars; for they ſhew the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of ill manners, which <hi>per accidens</hi> begot them, and they are likely to make them worſe, becauſe they being appointed to amend them, are diſappointed and diſabled by their owne croſſe contrarieties. As in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body, over-growne and over-flowne with ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. If a Philoſopher that conſiders onely a body nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſick nor well, giues that which is good. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:10388:41"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> calls it) and when he hath done an Emperick come that conſiders it as ſick, but he knowes not of what, nor the temper of the conſtitution, but boldly and blindly giues one medicine to all, for all diſeaſes, and at laſt the judicious Phyſitian come and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it as it is, and know what to doe, hee muſt firſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe all the other haue done, before hee dare adminiſter that which ſhould firſt haue beene taken, and by this time, the body is either paſt cure, or deſperate concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons muſt be tried to recover it. Therefore happy is our State Eccleſiaſticall, in whoſe Convocation our ſupream Soveraign is Preſident, ſo that the Lawes paſſing with his royall conſent, are certaine, and eaſie to be obeyed, by reaſon of their rareneſſe and paucitie, which makes them pertinent, diſtinct, and free from confuſion. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I doe not a little marveile at learned <hi>Baronius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baronius An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Anno. <hi>528.</hi>
               </note> that ſince hee doth not deny <hi>Iuſtinianus</hi> the Emperour the power of making Eccleſiaſticall Lawes, he ſhould ſo ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſly and buſily inquire, what ſhould moue him to meddle with the making of them; when as I doe not doubt, but the Clergie then might requeſt him to it. This laſt act of ſupremacie, is to receiue appeales, and giue determinate deciſions, and this hath its effect, and is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts. And they doe not exerciſe any power, that is not derived from this ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, either immediately, or mediately. So that as the lawes they execute, are the Kings Eccleſiaſticall Lawes, ſo theſe Courts are the Kings, and all the proceſſes and courſes approved by his Majeſties Lawes. Therefore now there is no ground for a <hi>praemunire</hi> in them, though the words of the Statute runne <hi>(to Rome or elſe-where)</hi> for by (elſe-where) ſeemes to be meant, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> power,<note place="margin">Babylonem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gallicam, vt Petrarch. epiſt. <hi>123.</hi>
               </note> or Court, which was not then at <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe the Popes ſeat was then at <hi>Avignion</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and not our Biſhops conſiſtorie: For I beleeue, that Statute was
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:10388:41"/> made to free them as well from the forraine vſurpation, as any other of the King Courts, as the pragmaticall ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>France</hi> doth, which was of the nature, and in imitation of it about the ſame time, by <hi>Charles</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, brother-in-law to <hi>Edward</hi> the third. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it was then meant, I am ſure it cannot extend to them now, vnleſſe wee will deny the Kings ſupremacie over all cauſes and perſons Eccleſiaſticall; and then they are not the Kings Courts; but if we grant the Kings ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, wee muſt deny that any of his Courts can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre a <hi>praemunire.</hi> A prohibition, I grant, may lawfully lye there, becauſe it is ſafe for the whole State, that every juriſdiction ſhould haue its bounds, and keep, or be kept in them. But yet I will not ſay ſo in generall, but we muſt admit them with diſtinction of prohibitions, one of Law, another of Fact. Now that prohibition which is of Law, according to the expreſſe words of the Statute, (which are commonly large enough) is the prohibition that is lawfull, as for a prohibition of fact, which is by a ſophiſticall ſuggeſtion ſucked and ſqueezed out of the copie of the libell, without judgment of the Kings Courts vpon it, in my opinion is not right, and is many times the cauſe of wrong, either in vnjuſtice or delayes; yea and in abuſing of the Statute with the Kings Courts. For the prohibition of law, the moſt I conceiue it inferres is, to make all the proceedings voide, <hi>Coram non Iudice.</hi> But if I might know, what degree and quality of offence it is, for a Court temporall to hold plea of a meere Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cauſe, I ſhould more eaſily apprehend the ſcandalous nature of the ground of a prohibition, which it may be, is the ſame with a writ of errour in the temporall Court; ſince that a conſultation doth not enſue vpon that, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a prohibition grounded vpon a ſuggeſtion. So then, all the proceedings of theſe Courts, haue their power from this laſt act of ſupremacie, as well in primatiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:10388:42"/> of inquiſition, as in punitiue proceſſes of execution. As this authentick authoritie is moſt ſeene in the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings <hi>ex officio,</hi> which are not onely, nor alwayes by oath, (as many are miſtaken.) Theſe are by immediate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, where an Eccleſiaſticall cauſe is criminall, and proſecuted as criminall: And ſo alſo the vtmoſt punitiue proceſſe Eccleſiaſticall, which is a writ <hi>de Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato capiendo,</hi> is evidently derived from the Kings power, and iſſueth immediately from his favour to the Church, that it may be more eaſily obeyed,<note place="margin">Iohan. de Pariſ. de Poteſtate Reg. Concl. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and is divers and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in ſundry governments, and executed by temporall power, being nothing of the nature of the ſpirituall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, but an acceſſion <hi>conceſſâ permiſsione ex devotione Principum</hi> (as <hi>Iohannes de Pariſiis</hi> ſaith againſt <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight.) As for the judgements of Biſhops conſiſtories, as they are derived from the power and law of Chriſt the great Biſhop: ſo they are like the jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of them, who are rather arbiters <hi>&amp; amicabiles com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitores</hi> (as <hi>Panormitane</hi>) then Iudges, ruling by the auſterity of authority, ſo that poore defendants may flie to them, as to their altars, who are Miniſters of the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: and in this ſenſe, that which <hi>Architas</hi> ſpeakes is moſt true,<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Idem eſſe arbitrum &amp; Aram.</hi> And though they haue no forcing power, but from the King, and no power of any force againſt the King; yet the greateſt and beſt Kings haue yeelded to them in their advice, not as Prelates, but as they are Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in God, (as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ſaid to his father King <hi>Philip</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Dion. Chryſoſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> who will rule the higheſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and yet profeſſe themſelues ſervants of ſervants; which makes mee call to minde, the obſervation of the wiſeſt King <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Proverb. 30.</note> that one of the chiefeſt inſtruments whereby the earth is ſhaken, is, a ſervant that rules over Princes. And as they vſurpe rule, ſo they vſurpe the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:10388:42"/> ſword of temporall Princes, and carry it in the ſpirituall ſcabbard; and drawing it, doe more hurt in their paſſion, then they can help by their priviledge; when as they found it ſoberly and orderly put up by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> when Chriſt was at his elbow to heale the greateſt wound that hee could make. Thus is it ſomewhat plaine, how Eccleſiaſticall power is derived from the King, as hee is ſupreame head in lawfull and full authority over all cauſes and perſons; which double power in my conceit, the cuſtome of the ancient <hi>Perſians</hi> at the death of their Monarch doth fully and fitly expreſſe, for the lawes are ſilent:<note place="margin">Briſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Regn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yea and their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their holy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall fire which every one worſhiped in his private houſe as his houſhold god, was put out when the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour died.</p>
            <p n="4">§ 4 The next thing which I promiſed to declare, was how the honour of the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall is annexed to the power by the Kings lawes and royall prorogatiue. The honour of the Clergy is contained in revenewes and priviledges,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> which are vnited to their powers of order and juriſdiction; which powers although we ſhould grant that ſimply conſidered in themſelues, they are not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed <hi>jure divino;</hi> yet I am ſure none will deny that they are diſtinct, <hi>quoad extenſionem, permiſſione &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batione divinâ,</hi> as <hi>Iohannes de Pariſiis</hi> doth diſtinguiſh the power given the Apoſtles into ſix parts, in reſpect of ſo many ſeverall acts of execution, the fift of which is <hi>poteſtas diſpoſitionis miniſtrorum, ſecundum quoſdam quoad determinationem juriſdictionis Eccleſiaſticae ut vitetur con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſio.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. de cap. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> And as they are thus diſtinct according to the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and ſtand ſo confirmed by the poſitiue lawes of the land; ſo they haue diſtinct portions and priviledges according to the ſame lawes: yet after a different man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, eſpecially in reſpect of the portion. For the power of order which hath maintenance of diverſe kindes, as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:10388:43"/> tithes, oblations, Gleabland and mortuaries holds them all according to the lawes of this land, as due to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, for executing the power of order, but by different acts of theſe lawes; as Mortuaries are permitted, and Gleablands granted, Tithes and Oblations confirmed, and all conſtrained to be paid. Now tithes that are onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Kings poſitiue lawes, are ſuppoſed to bee due by ſome other law of higher nature then the Kings, which is not any forraine law,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Cler. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Ius Eccleſiaſticum</hi> (as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> calls the Cannon law) it muſt bee then by law divine; or immediately ariſing from ſupernaturall and morall conſiderations, which law we grant to be poſitiue; yet not meerely humaine,<note place="margin">Hooker Eccleſ. Polit. l. <hi>1. §. 15.</hi>
               </note> nor changeable in reſpect to us: and they muſt neceſſarily runne into many groſſe errours, that take onely ſuch lawes for poſitiue as are invented by men; and thence conclude them mutable. And therefore I preſume that the learned <hi>Selden</hi> doth ſo vnderſtand the poſitiue law, by which hee holds tithes to be due, not in oppoſition to divine and morall; but as ſpecially diverſe from it (as it partly appeares in the whole drift of his hiſtory) where I doe not beleeue that any can finde that hee ever delivers his judgement, denying them to bee <hi>jure divino:</hi> ſo that in my apprehenſion, and I hope not againſt his intention, he may doe the Church much good in his relating what wrongs the Clergy in all ages haue ſuſtained. For his hiſtory is onely <hi>de facto,</hi> what hath beene done; hee giues not his judgement <hi>de iure</hi> what ought to haue beene done, which if he had, he would aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly haue pronounced for them; and this I am forced to beleeue, when I conſider his exact generall knowledge, and the reverent reſpect he beares to authentique antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. I doe not in this confeſſe that they are not <hi>iure divino,</hi> becauſe I affirme not them to be due by the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that is no direct conſequence vpon my propoſition; for not onely the judiciall law which was the commend, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:10388:43"/> I beleeue in moſt points is ſtill the counſaile of the moſt wiſe God (eſpecially in this particular where the ground of the command is morall) doth proportion a tenth part as neceſſary then to be paid; and though the ſame neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty binds vs not now, yet the correſpondencie of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencie (as I conceiue) doth hold vs as ſtrongly to it as it did that ſtate. For I ſee no inconvenience in tithes-paying in our ſtate more then in theirs, but onely they were brought home vnto Prieſts (which onely exception M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cartwright</hi> makes againſt tithes:<note place="margin">Annot. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Teſt. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>) But I ſtand not onely vpon this, but I am alſo partly perſwaded, that they were confirmed by Apoſtolicall approbation, though it bee not in expreſſe words ſo ſet downe. For though the Apoſtles did all preach the Goſpell, yet they did not all write, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did thoſe that did write commit all to writing which they did teach:<note place="margin">2 Theſ.</note> for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to keepe the traditions they had beene taught either by word or epiſtle. And therefore it is freely acknowledged by a famous Orthodox divine of our owne, <hi>non omnia eſſe ſcripta in libris voteris &amp; novi Teſtamenti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whittak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bellar. q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quae Apoſtoli aut docuerunt aut fecerunt; ſed fatemur Apoſtolos ritus &amp; conſuetudines ſanxiſſe, non autem ſcripſiſſe;</hi> hence it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that they might by conſent confirme them, becauſe it was not onely a cuſtome and a law then in force, and they did not delight to innovate, but vpon neceſſitie: but alſo becauſe we doe not finde one word of their abrogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or alteration. Yea it ſeemes to mee that the author of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> entitles the Miniſters of the Goſpell to them by a more particular right,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.</note> (as Biſhop <hi>Andrewes</hi> calls it) <hi>jure Benedictionis,</hi> for it is not onely ſaid that <hi>Abraham</hi> paid <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> tithes as hee was the higheſt Prieſt,<note place="margin">Benedixit tantùm v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vatus ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione, ſed perior ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritate.</note> but that hee received them and bleſſed him; which implyes bleſſing to be the duty he performed for them. And whatſoever wee hold of theſe tithes, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelfe the Primitiue Church did ſo conclude, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:10388:44"/> they would not with ſuch a generall conſent haue bound themſelues to that meanes and portion of mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. I ſpeake of the Church <hi>in ſtatu pacato,</hi> it was otherwiſe with them I confeſſe <hi>in ſtatu perturbato,</hi> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; but not out of good choiſe, but hard chance: For obſerue but from the firſt generall Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> (not to reckon vpon Provincall Synods, becauſe they doe not bind our ſtate but onely in point of doctrine and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample) peruſe them till the laſt of the <hi>Lateraine,</hi> and you ſhall finde they are plaine and peremptory. And not onely in the acts which in ſome Councells are erroneous, (as in the ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice</hi>) being the ſeaventh ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, there is a Cannon very particularly paſſed with a generall conſent; ſo in the Councell of <hi>Lateraine</hi> vnder <hi>Innocent</hi> the third,<note place="margin">Balſomon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Nicen. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo can. <hi>12.</hi> Concil. Later. <hi>4.</hi> can. <hi>54.</hi>
               </note> where it is particularly ſet downe, that the Engliſh Ambaſſadors were preſent. There is a Canon that runs thus, <hi>Statuimus quòd ſolutio decimarum praecedat exactionem tributorum.</hi> We haue nationall Councells alſo as at moſt Coronations of the Kings before the conqueſt, and alſo immediately vpon the conqueſt; and many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Charters wherein tithes haue beene confirmed to the Clergy, and that with ſolemne vowes and imprecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which dedication to God, if there be no other divine right, puts the detainers of them into <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra's</hi> caſe;<note place="margin">Acts 5.</note> becauſe that though while it was wholy with them, it was their owne; yet when it was thus ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by their ſolemne vowes, then ſanctified by the ſolemne act of Biſhops; not onely ratifying the Founders vow, but conſecrating them with the Church to divine vſes, the nature, property, with the propriety was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. So that I will conclude from theſe premiſes, that the poſitiue law by which tithes are due to the Clergie, is not meerely humane but mixt and preternaturall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it binds men as they are members of the ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſociety of the Church viſible: and becauſe they haue
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:10388:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> bound themſelues by it in divine conſiderations. But yet they are enjoyed by the confirmation and conſtraining power of the Kings lawes: And were it not for the lawes, as they are an vndoubted due, ſo they would be a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all debt with many; and that out of ſeverall grounds: ſome deſiring to haue ſtipends in ſtead of tithes, doe too willingly remit them for a ſufficient ſtipend though it bee vncertaine, eſpecially to their ſucceſſors. But I hope this ground will never be generall, as long as this Kingdome is a Monarchie, for if it is a miſerie of free Cities and Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracies,<note place="margin">Ariſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>4.</hi> cap.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> — yet I muſt needs confeſſe that at the firſt originall of Vicarages they had but ſtipends, but it was vnjuſt;<note place="margin">Linwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cio Vica roch.</note> 
               <hi>Vicarii ſtipendio ſunt contenti,</hi> which was but a permitting provinciall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Another meanes whereby the due payment of tithes is impeached, is, the cuſtomes of many places: which are lawfull and laudable with theſe conditions; if they were not the inventions of men, but begotten by time, and if they be as reaſonable as ancient;<note place="margin">Cujaciu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pus Vlpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nam debent eſſe tàm ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſariae continuatione quàm rectae in ortu:</hi> and where the law is defectiue, for cuſtomes againſt law are voyd by the Civill law, if they bee not expreſly confirmed by the ſupreame power. With theſe conditions let cuſtomes be enjoyed.<note place="margin">L. Sacra Q. de leg</note> But the next pretenſe is preſcription againſt tithes once paid, and that we may admit with his limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; as that it extend not to thoſe things that cannot be alienate, that are annexed to the Crowne,<note place="margin">Dier. rep <hi>31<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</hi>
               </note> or if it ſtand not <hi>contra ſtatutum poſtea editum,</hi> and be granted vpon a good cuſtome, and the perſon qualified, to poſſeſſe the thing claimed; for lawfull preſcription cannot proceed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out as lawfull poſſeſſion. The want of theſe lawfull limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations made the Councell of <hi>Laterane</hi> vnder <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, condemne and controule the grand preſcription of <hi>Clyentary</hi> tithes continued from <hi>Charles Martellus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Duarenus nef. l. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The taking away of which ſhirking ſhifts made many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:10388:45"/> another, which priviledge is either of ſocieties or perſons, granting immunities from payment of tithes, which pretenſe of all others (as far as I vnderſtand) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee made good by the moſt favourable forced inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation that may be; for they are void and nullified ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all the reſtraining Proviſoes that bound a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge. For they were granted againſt the law of God and nature, not onely beſides it; there are ſome revoked by the ſame power that granted them, as <hi>Innocent</hi> the third in the fourth Councell of <hi>Laterane.</hi> And in this particular Kingdome <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth made many ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes to reſtraine thoſe priviledges granted to the Friers,<note place="margin">4. <hi>Hen.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> eſpecially providing that none ſhould haue any <hi>de novo;</hi> but that which proues them void in this Kingdome, is, that not onely the particular perſons, but alſo their whole ſocieties are diſſolved and diſtroyed; and ſo they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired and extinguiſhed with them:<note place="margin">Bartolus in D. Q. Sodales. tit. <hi>24.</hi> Idem ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>Deſtructo Collegio pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reunt privilegia,</hi> eſpecially when their revenewes are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcate, <hi>&amp; non privilegiatus praeſcriptione, non ſuccedat pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegiato.</hi> But when other meanes began to be reſtrained, they procured appropriations and annexions of benefices preſentatiue, not onely in point of patronage, but alſo they tooke the whole due without diſcharging any of the duty; which laſt and worſt pretenſe I will not deny but the wit of man may make it plauſible, yet I am ſure it will never bee pleaſing to the will of God. Monkes and Friars were the authors of theſe immunities and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations, (to omit cuſtomes and preſcriptions, becauſe they doe not ſo much wrong, and haue more ground of right:) I doe not accuſe the Monkes who lived in the firſt fiue hundred yeares after Chriſt, who lived holy, and laboured in their callings, and had no ſuch priviledges: Neither doe I condemne <hi>Benedict</hi> who was the father and firſt founder of all that profeſſed a regular life in a ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred cloyſter in the Weſtern Church.<note place="margin">Hoſpinianus de origine Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat.</note> For he had good
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:10388:45"/> reaſon ſo to doe, conſidering the tumults and many broiles that fell out vnder the government of <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> &amp; by reaſon of the continuall incurſions of the barbarous nations into <hi>Italy.</hi> But when he was thus ſhut vp, many reſorted vnto him, admiring his devotion; at laſt they tooke rules from him, and grew into a fraternitie of the Benedictines: and from them ſprang many other orders; who living a life far different from other men, bred great wonderment in all, and that admiration procured adoration of their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; made thoſe that were able beſtow great revenewes vpon them: Yea they did ſo dote vpon them, that after a while they endowed them, if not with the greateſt, yet I am ſure the beſt and fatteſt part of their Countryes; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that moſt of the moſt pious Princes of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome were forced to make a ſtatute of Mortmaine, (like <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo.</note> who made the firſt ſtatute of Mortmaine) for theſe revenewes which they poſſeſſed were in a dead hand, that did no good to the Common-wealth. Whence we may obſerue that this ſtatute was rather for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Common-wealth, then made out of the diſlike of the Church meanes; eſpecially ſince theſe Friers were not of the Clergie, but meere Lay-men; and the Clergy had as much reaſon to deſire a law for Amortization as the Common-wealth, becauſe as they had conferred lands and goods vpon them, (for not onely Princes, but Popes were taken with admiration of them) ſo they were alſo more charged with the publique, and had leſſe meanes. And this ſtatute gaue the occaſion to them to procure pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and immunities from payment of tithes. For though at firſt for a time they came to their Pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yet when they procured to haue Churches or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels of eaſe for their fraternities; then they obtained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Alexander</hi> the third in the <hi>Laterane</hi> Councell, when hee condemned preſcription,<note place="margin">Dua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nef. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to be confirmed priviledged from payment of tithes of thoſe lands which they tilled
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:10388:46"/> themſelues; when as <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth our country-man, his immediate predeceſſor had revoked or reſtrained the immunities granted to them by <hi>Paſchall</hi> the ſecond.<note place="margin">Flavius Chen. Compend. Bulla tom. <hi>1.</hi> Paſchal.</note> But when <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, who loved to bee doing and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, reſtrained the grant of <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, which they perceived did much prejudice their plentifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, they procured diſpenſations from the Pope to haue parſonages appropriate to their houſes in more great abundance. For I deny not but ſome were annexed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as to the Abbey of Crowland, and others; yet theſe were granted more by the Popes licence then the Princes authoritie. And then began the Schoolmen to entangle the right of tithes, and their curioſitie and their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe enabled them, and put them vpon it: for when vnder <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, they multiplyed into multitude, (as there were ſixteene orders ſet vp in that Century) and hee limited and leſſened their revenewes, they ſought to maintaine that by right which before they had obtained by wrong, and retained by protection and priviledge. Then began the contention betweene the Schoolmen and the Cannoniſts about the right of tithes; and I conceiue <hi>Innocent</hi> the third to be of the Canoniſts part, becauſe he was the firſt great advancer of them in the Church, and no free friend to the Friars. This I haue conceived by comparing Church hiſtories with the Cannon law, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Decretalls: theſe wrongs of the Clergie were ſo brought in and vpheld, ſo continued in our Kingdome till <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth of famous memorie; who either inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a reformation in religion, ſeiſed vpon the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues of religious houſes; or ayming at their revenewes ſet vpon, rather then finiſhed a reformation, confiſcated them to his vſe, as eſcheated as their lands were, and ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vpon their appropriations which were not theirs; but morgaged as it were <hi>in commendam</hi> to them, and he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed the Crowne of them, and ſold them to private men;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:10388:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> which hold them by as much right as the Monaſteries did, &amp; no better. Though ſome would willingly perſwade themſelues that they hold them by as right and juſt law, as they doe any purchaſed inheritance; for they ſay, though they were once ſpirituall, yet now they are made temporall, &amp; lay-fees by the lawes of diſſolution; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the two and thirtieth of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth. It is true that thoſe ſtatutes apply diverſe law termes, (I will not call them meere law fictions) to thoſe things that properly belong to temporall inheritances, and haue made them demandable by originall writs, and given order of conveyance, by deed, fine, and act of Parliament; which act, as it is booteleſſe, ſo it is contumacie in any private ſubject to queſtion: onely thus much I hope I may ſay without generall offence, ſince I conceiue it the truth, and yet not all the truth; I doe not yet vnderſtand how that can bee made manifeſt to bee a free Parliament in that point. For I doe not beleeue, that the lower Houſe did either propoſe, or generally approue it, though they aſſented to it. Neither doe I thinke, that King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight did freely propound it out of his owne choyce, but that the neceſſity of the preſent time did put him vpon it. And I hope he intended to call it in, if hee had lived. As <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the King of <hi>Syra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſa</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> when his treaſure waxed too ſhort for a great imployment: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Poly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Strat</note> hee commanded to take the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Aſclepius</hi> his temple, and to proclaime them to be ſold in the market, as profane and common commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which the <hi>Syracuſans</hi> were very eager to buy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had Church-bargaines. But when hee had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what his neceſſity required, he preſently ſent forth an edict, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that if any one had bought thoſe devoted treaſures, they ſhould againe reſtore them to the Church. This courſe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:10388:47"/> had beene ſomewhat juſt, if hee had let them enjoy the treaſures, vntill they might haue regained by them what they coſt, (as perhaps moſt purchaſers of Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue.) But that which moſt hinders me from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending it to be a free pure act, is, becauſe the moſt actiue and ſpirituall part in Parliament, was pittifully paſsiue in it, it was at beſt mixt by reaction in the patient Clergie, who did neither abſolutely obey, nor reſolutely reſiſt, but ſilently ſuffer that to paſſe, which was not right; and therefore the act was not free from wrong. Neither doe many of the judicious ſages of our law ſo fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue of it.<note place="margin">Conſideration 6.</note> Yea S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> in his conſiderations of the Clergie of <hi>England,</hi> dedicated to King <hi>Iames</hi> of peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able memory, confeſſes, that hee was of opinion, that all the Parliaments, ſince the twenty ſeventh, and thirtie one of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, ſtand obnoxious and bound in conſcience to God, to doe ſomewhat for the Church, to reduce that patrimonie; or, that ſince they haue debarred the Church of her dowry, they ſhould make her a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent joynture. Which opinion of his, is more ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in my apprehenſion, and advantageouſly pertinent than theirs, who onely enveigh againſt the Parliament, and <hi>Henry</hi> the eight the head and ruler of it: which act (admitting the neceſsity then that vrged him to vſe the power of Eccleſiaſticall dominion) is not altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, (though this reformation did more wrong to the Clergie, than the conqueſt:) For what he was to do, was to be done in haſte; and in that routing-ruſh of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, who could expect but the part corrected, muſt needs be for the time, neere to vtter ruine; though hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely, if the author of the reformation had lived to finiſh it, amends would haue beene made in ſome meaſure. But <hi>Henry</hi> the eight did rather put down the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, than ſet vp ours; as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great pulled downe the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchie, but ſet not vp the <hi>Grecian.</hi> But to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:10388:47"/> pull downe one was the onely way to ſet vp another; as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> rooted out all the opinions of the former Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, to ſet vp his owne; or as <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> who being their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Zetzes</hi> in his <hi>Chiliads</hi>) he burned the bookes of all the ancient Phiſicians, to ſet vs his owne,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chil.</hi> 155.</note> or theirs as his. So that if a publick reformer begin once to alter, he muſt of neceſſity, for the time, ſtirre, if not remoue more than hee firſt intended, eſpecially if hee be croſſed and curbed by an adverſary, that ſtands ſtrongeſt by that part which needs reformation, and by that in it, which will beſt helpe him in the performing of it. For he that will prevaile againſt an incroaching enemy, that hath a party in his kingdome, muſt be ſure with all apt induſtrie, to obſerue and oppoſe him in his counſels, by bereaving him of his counſellers and agents, either by taking them away at once, or putting them as exiles from him, or pulling them to himſelfe, which is the ſafeſt and honourableſt courſe. Now the Pope, who was the abſolute inſolent adverſary to <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, ſtood by the Monkiſh part of the Clergie, and chiefly by their rich revenues; and therefore, it behoved the King, either to reconcile them to himſelfe, or vtterly to ruine them (as fell out becauſe they rebelled.) And in the perſecution of them, hee ranne a cleane contrary courſe to the Pope. As I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, when <hi>Cyrus</hi> tooke <hi>Babylon,</hi> he drew <hi>Euphrates</hi> drie, and made all land; And <hi>Xerxes</hi> when he went againſt <hi>Athens,</hi> would haue made all ſea,<note place="margin">Dion. C <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: So <hi>Henry</hi> the eight made all Lay and land, when hee intended to be free from the vſurpation of the Pope, and the Pope made all ſpirituall and his See, when hee aymed at his abſolute vnreſtrained extravigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie both in See and Scepter. This heat and height of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition made the King proceed too farre, which, I beleeue, hee did ſomewhat perceiue, in that he did retract in ſome
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:10388:48"/> particulars, from the firſt courſe: As in erecting ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall Seats, and more Cathedrall Churches, out of the ruines of Monaſteries and Priories. And in that hee made of the appropriation of <hi>Royſton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">33. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</note> a Pariſh-Church. And I preſume, he might haue proceeded farther, if hee had not beene ſoone after cut off by death, and hindred by profane and ſacrilegious inſtruments while he lived, who, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe, were the ſame men and meanes, that tried to procure the diſſolution of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> by act of Parliament, during the nonage of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth. So that the vnhappineſſe of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men judge by the event, not knowing the intent (as <hi>Paulus Iovius</hi> exclaimes of him.<note place="margin">Iovius de vir. illuſt.</note>) In my minde, hee may be well paralelled with <hi>Charles Martellus,</hi> the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of the Church, who, when hee defended the Pope, was the firſt that was called <hi>Chriſtianiſſimus</hi> among the <hi>French</hi> Kings, by <hi>Gregory</hi> the third; yet hee was the firſt that robbed the Clergie in <hi>France,</hi> by giving <hi>Clientary</hi> tythes,<note place="margin">Baronius Anno <hi>759.</hi>
               </note> which they call <hi>feudall</hi> to his followers: yea and hee depoſed the Archbiſhop of <hi>Reemes,</hi> and diſpoſed of the Biſhoprick to one <hi>Miloeo Caualeire.</hi> So <hi>Henry</hi> the eight had firſt the title of the Defender of the Faith, for publiſhing a booke againſt <hi>Luther,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellarm. de ſcript. Eccleſ.</note> which (<hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith) <hi>Roffenſis</hi> wrote, and preſently after fell foule vpon the Clergie. So that, (I beleeue) the Pope repented of the title, and was ready, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to giue him ſo good a title, as his predeceſſour <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond gaue <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth of <hi>France,</hi> in his Bull, which <hi>Guicciardine</hi> notes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed of malice,<note place="margin">Guicc. hiſt. l. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nella nominon dolo, non piu Chriſtianiſsimo, ma illuſtriſsimo.</hi> But let him be as bad as they will make him, yet I dare excuſe him, as <hi>Baronius</hi> doth <hi>Martellus,</hi> and ſay of him as <hi>Guicciardine</hi> ſaid of the Popes,<note place="margin">Guicc. Hypomn. Polit. <hi>123.</hi>
               </note> that hee was an honeſt man, becauſe he was not more wicked than moſt men. I haue in this as farre as I am able with a good conſcience, cleared our State from the forraine fame of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:10388:48"/> ſacriledge. But I cannot free particular men from it, which haue no pretence for what they detaine, or take from the Clergie, but onely that they are not convinced that there is ſuch a ſinne as ſacriledge; and that becauſe they hold not tythes due <hi>iure divino,</hi> and that becauſe they deſire ſtill to hold them by the law of the land. And that they may more colourably continue it, they hold no ſuch ſinne as Symonie, that the preſented may make a ſymonaicall contract, whereby they are confirmed and corroborated in their ſacrilegious vſurpations. But I will not diſpute the poynt, whether there be any ſuch ſinne as Symonie, in relation to a private preſentation without reſpect to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders taken with it. But I am ſure, none will deny, but where is a ſymonaicall contract, there is perjurie in the Inſtituted. As for ſacriledge, I grant it is not eaſie for men that are guilty of it, to be convinced that it is a ſinne. For ſinnes of omiſſion cannot ſo quickly and ſharply, touch the conſcienee, becauſe they are the breach of an affirmatiue law, which doth not ſo ſtrongly check the vice, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to the dutie; eſpecially when pleaſure or profit haue bribed the judgement. For I feare, ſome hold ſtolne tythes, the ſweeteſt part of their inheritance, as it is ſaid by the Epicures;<note place="margin">Zetzes Chil. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: who doting vpon voluptuous ſweet delicates, called hony the tenth part of the <hi>Ambroſia;</hi> and perhaps that ſect ſet vp the trade of Bee-mongers in <hi>Athens,</hi> (as <hi>Syneſius</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Syneſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 136.</note> So I am afraid, the tickling ſweetneſſe of tythes, is the cauſe, why the ſmart and ſowrneſſe of ſacriledge is not felt, nor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. And therefore, in my opinion,<note place="margin">Thom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> q. <hi>155.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> doth well, to make ſacriledge, <hi>ſpeciem luxuriae;</hi> ſo that it may be a ſinne, and yet they never be convinced of it. I am ſure, not onely the ancient Fathers of the moſt pure primitiue Church, but even the godly Emperours did eſteeme it a ſinne, and that in a high degree, that when
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:10388:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> they granted generall pardons at Eaſter, and other ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, they excepted ſacrilegious perſons: As <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the great,<note place="margin">Theod. tit. de Indulg. Crim.</note> 
               <hi>ob diem Paſchae, quem intimo corde celebramus, quos reatus aſtringit, carcer incluſit, ſolvimus; attamen ſacrilegus maximè à communione iſtius munieris ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paretur:</hi> So alſo <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian; Religio anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariae obſervationis hortatur, vt omnes periculo carceris, &amp; à metu poenarum eximi iubeamus: verùm eos excipimus, quos ſcelera graviora compulerunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. eodem tit.</note> 
               <hi>vt qui ſunt ſacrilegi &amp; ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chri violatores.</hi> So in many of the Novels; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, vpon Eaſter day ſet all perſons free <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Harmenopulus Promp. Iur. Civ. l. <hi>6.</hi> tit. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> but if any be guilty of ſacriledge, ſet him be kept ſtill in hold. So that you ſee, it was reckoned <hi>inter extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria crimina</hi> in thoſe dayes; and ſo it would be thought with vs, if profit did not blinde the judgement in the payer of tythes, and indiſcreet covetouſneſſe leade many Clergy-men to make no diſtinction betwixt free and friendly compoſitions with a bountifull Patron and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. In my poore judgement, the Canon Law is but juſt,<note place="margin">Quicunque c. <hi>6.</hi> q. de Iur. Patronatus.</note> in decreeing, that <hi>Si patronus Laicus ad inopiam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit redactus,</hi> hee muſt haue ſome competent ſuſtenance from the incumbent, eſpecially if he haue not beene ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious, and ſo by Gods judgement brought to it. And I doe conceiue, that this may be, notwithſtanding they doe not charge any parſonage with annuitie rents, which is prohibited by the ſtatute of <hi>Elizab.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 2.</note> Thus it is plaine, that the revenues and maintenance of the Clergie are poſſeſſed by the Kings Lawes, and may be demanded as due by them.</p>
            <p n="5">§. 5. The other part of the honour of the Clergie, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the power of order, is in priviledges, &amp; immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, by which this power is exerciſed with more eaſe, delight, and reſpect; and, as it were, with the whole man without diſtraction. Now all the priviledges the Church doth enjoy or deſire, ariſe, and are raiſed by the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:10388:49"/> Kings lawes, and royall prerogatiue. As that ancient-of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten-confirmed <hi>Magna Charta</hi> doth fully confirme all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer priviledges of the Clergie.<note place="margin">Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ta cap</note> And that was then favour enough, for then they had priviledges to a ſurfeiting ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſſage, but now the Clergie ſtands in more need of them, and they humbly expect them onely from the favour of their Prince, who hath a plenitude of power, to grant more and larger priviledges, than ever they will deſire. For all priviledges are granted in relation to ſome Law, and the power of an abſolute Prince is aboue all Lawes, (as <hi>Dion Chryſoſtome</hi> told juſt <hi>Trajane</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Dion <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cujac vat. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or as the ſame Counſellour to the ſame Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which <hi>Cujacius</hi> explaines and limits to coactiue correctiue Lawes, which <hi>Dion</hi> ſaith, began in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> dayes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">Dion</note> none of the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> were freed from lawes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is from the neceſſity of obeying. And I doe beleeue, that the Scriptures (ſeeing that they ſay more for the right of Kings, than any booke in the world) doe, if not fully ſet downe this power, yet permit it with approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſome caſes, eſpecially for the publick good of the Church, which, I am ſure, is a farre more conſcionable and commendable courſe, than to accommodate religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſerue the turne of the State (as that judicious <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus</hi> vpon <hi>Tacitus) Biſogna accommodar la ragione di ſtato alla religione, &amp; nan la religione, alla ragione di ſtato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our King then being a moſt abſolute Monarch, hath this prerogatiue, and from that wee haue and hold our priviledges, not from that written prerogatiue, abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of <hi>Fitzherberts</hi> Abridgement, by S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Stanford,</hi> whereby the Kings Exchequer hath many pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and peculiar proceſſes (as the Civilians call them <hi>privilegia fiſci, fiſcus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>habet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cujaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſerv. l. <hi>2</hi>
               </note>) But from an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written vnreſtrained right of dominion, whereby he hath
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:10388:50"/> plenarie power, not onely to make legall propoſitions of validitie, or voyde in their firſt inſtitution, or to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret them either by declaring them to bee corrected in ſome poyntes and caſes, eſpecially if hee correct them by a more particular expreſſe preſſing law, as hee may correct the law of nature by the law of nations; the law of nations, by the law of armes; the law of armes, by the law of particular Leagues; and all by the power of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion: or reſtraine them in reſpect of ſome perſons, or publick ſocieties; but he may diſpence alſo with them, ſince ſome penall ſtatutes are made with relation to his power of pardon after the act; therefore it is not ſo much to exempt them from being obnoxious to the puniſhment, by pre-interpreting that it was not intended to extend to ſuch perſons; for ſo the priviledge is not againſt law, but beſides it, or aboue it. Yea there are ſtatutes diſpenſato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; as that of the pluralitie, and non recidencie which the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> limits by his approbation.<note place="margin">Eccl. Anglicanae Canon. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note> And priviledges muſt neceſſarily bee where there are multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of ſtatutes, which be ſo ſtrict in point of injunction, as if the makers of them had not conſidered, that poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique lawes muſt be made with reſpect to morall poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, as what men may doe; and yet the puniſhment of their tranſgreſſion is not expreſſed, but left to the pleaſure or diſpleaſure of the King. But theſe are not the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that the Kings royall prerogatiue doth grant, as immunities and impunities, for then the lawes ſhould bee onely punitine, if there were onely vſe of protections and pardons: but as lawes are alſo remuneratiue, ſo Princes haue power to reward after a priviledging manner, and chiefly in our Kingdome, where it ſeemes to be on purpoſe omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the written lawes, and left to the Kings pleaſure and power; eſpecially concerning Eccleſiaſticall perſons, who haue moſt neede of them, and may now as freely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them as any other perſons. For though heretofore
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:10388:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> it was prejudiciall to our Kings to grant priviledges to all Eccleſiaſticall perſons, when they were ſo encreaſed in multitudes, and overgrowne in magnitude for the whole Kingdome, and the Popes would confirme them as irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable: yet now they are but few in number and ſmall in power, and the King may call them in when hee pleaſes. This want of theſe priviledges hath beene the cauſe of much evill in the Church, and the more they are impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by thoſe that profeſſe themſelues the maintainers of the Kings peace, lawes, and royall prerogatiue, the more will the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall runne to ruine. And they are much infringed in our Vniverſities, which I am forced to complaine of, with feare, leſt that fall out which happened to the Vniverſitie of <hi>Prague;</hi> which was vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruined by <hi>Charles</hi> the fift, taking the priviledges away at <hi>Don Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is</hi> deſire. Whereas <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France</hi> fearing and favouring the Vniverſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored all the priviledges which <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh had taken away vpon a juſt ground of ſedition,<note place="margin">Dino hiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which hath made it to reviue and flouriſh ever ſince. But there are ſome politiques that hold it a needleſſe thing, to bee any way indulgent to ſilly Schollers,<note place="margin">Cuja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſent. <hi>1.</hi> tit</note> as <hi>Cujacius</hi> ſaith out of <hi>Galen,</hi> that they expreſſed weake men vnder the title of <hi>ſcholaſtici:</hi> they make meere <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Iohn a noakes of them, but the fault is in themſelues according to the <hi>French</hi> Proverbe, <hi>Qui ſe fait brebis le l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>up la mange:</hi> For though the Clergie bee weake of it ſelfe, and tempt the contemners of it to over-top and over-turne it: Yet ſince we haue a pious prudent Prince, that is royally rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy vpon the firſt appeale, to protect and relieue his poore Clergie: we are not to be pittied, if we neglect to implore his ſupreame aſſiſtance. And thus it is ſomething evident how the honour of the Clergie annexed to the power of order, is granted and ſuſtained by the Kings lawes and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:10388:51"/> royall prerogatiue. I muſt now in briefe ſhew the like of the honour annexed to the power of juriſdiction.</p>
            <p n="6">§ 6 The power of juriſdiction which I doe here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, is not that deligated power which is in Biſhops, Vicars, or Officialls; nor that power Archdeacons and Deanes enjoy, either by cuſtome or priviledge: but that ordinary power which is in Biſhops. To this power of juriſdiction there is honour annexed by the lawes of this land, and the Kings royall prerogatiue: which I divide as before, into revenewes ordinary, and priviledges; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewes are their temporalls, and part of the perquiſits, called the <hi>Cenſus Cathedraticus:</hi> the firſt of which are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and granted by the Kings royall bounty, &amp; confirmed by the lawes; the other are ſet downe and approved by the ſame lawes. Biſhops temporalls are annexed to their ſees by the Kings gift,<note place="margin">Stanford prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogat. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and are as it were their Gleab, but are indeed their Baronies which they hold of the King <hi>in capite,</hi> and performe ſervices for them; and therefore they are as it were wards to the King during the vacancie: <hi>quae ratione Baroniae</hi> (as <hi>Linwood) ad Epiſcopum ſpectare poſſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Linwood de im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatib. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae. Duarenus de be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficijs. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dominus Rex cuſtodiam habet;</hi> (as <hi>Duarenus</hi> ſayes of the Kings of <hi>France) Princeps quàm diu vacat Epiſcopalis ſedes, feudorum lege, praediorum omnium adminiſtrationem ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</hi> But theſe temporalls are not to be reſtored till conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, and ſo ſeeme to be annexed to the power of order in Biſhops;<note place="margin">Auguſtinus de Ancona de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. P. P. quaeſt. <hi>22.</hi> Art. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> for their conſecration (according to the ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſticall Canoniſts) is but <hi>perfectio characteris,</hi> which they at firſt received when they tooke the order of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſo ſeeme not properly annexed to the power of juriſdiction: for before conſecration, vpon election and confirmation they may exerciſe the power of juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, though not of order. <hi>Epiſcopus electus &amp; confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus poteſt exercere quae ſunt juriſdictionis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Panormitan. in Decret. Ver. Conſ. <hi>§. 6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non quae ſunt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis Epiſcopalis ante conſecrationem,</hi> (as <hi>Othobone</hi> vpon
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:10388:51"/> 
               <hi>Linwood) ſuſpendere poteſt à beneficio, non ab officio;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Linwoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de conſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Glanvil cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quia ab officio ſuſpendere, eſt à poteſtate ordinis ordinaria.</hi> But Iuſtice <hi>Glanvil</hi> ſeemes to intimate that they were reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when they were but Lords elect, becauſe <hi>electi ante conſecrationem homagia ſua facere ſolent,</hi> but whether it were <hi>de jure</hi> or <hi>de gratia</hi> (as the learned in the Common law diſtinguiſh,) I leaue to them to determine; and thinke it great happineſſe for the Biſhops, and the great honour of our moderne Kings, that they are ſo fully reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at all, ſince they haue as much power, and may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend as much reaſon to ſeiſe the temporalls into their hands as well as others. — But our Royall Soveraignes pious Father,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               </note> ſet a good example to his Majeſtie to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; for in the firſt yeare of his raigne hee enacted a ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to prevent all diminution of Epiſcopall revenewes, though it were to alienate them to the vſe of his Crowne: yea though it were but in exchange for impropriations, (a courſe which was too common in Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes,) inſteed whereof our Kings haue out of royall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence given ſome licences for Mortmaines. If this redreſſe had come before they had beene too much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired: Biſhops would not haue deſired ſo many Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendams, nor Rectors of Pariſhes made vſe of the ſtatute of pluralitie. To their revenewes in theſe temporalls, there are many honourable priviledges annexed, as they are Barones; So that Biſhops haue the priviledges of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons in the Parliament, and that vpon good ground, ſince they hold of the King, and performe the ſervices belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them;<note place="margin">Mathew Hen. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> (as <hi>Mathew Paris) Epiſcopi de rege tenent in capite Baronias, &amp; faciunt omnes conſuetudines regis, &amp; ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut caeteri Barones debent intereſſe iudiciis regis cum Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</hi> Now the Biſhops (eſpecially ſince the reformation) are ready and willing, not onely to take the oath of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, which ſome denyed heretofore, as <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:10388:52"/> and <hi>Glanvill,</hi> who was the chiefe Iuſtice, ſeemes to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance it, by ſaying <hi>Epiſcopi conſecrati non ſolent Domino Regi homagium facere de Baroniis ſuis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Glanvil. lib. <hi>9.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed fidelitatem.</hi> The preſent Clergy I ſay is not onely ready to take the oath in the old favourable free forme, <hi>[ſalvo ordine,]</hi> but as it is now more ſtrictly obligatorie by putting in theſe words, <hi>[in verbo veritatis;]</hi> and leaving out the former. Which oath may be taken without any ſuſpicion of Symonie, (as <hi>Panormitan) Homagium, vel fidelitas ab Epiſcopo praeſtari poſſit, citra periculum Symoniae:</hi> and <hi>Cajetaine</hi> the learned ſchooleman doth in this agree with this ancient able Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſt;<note place="margin">Cajetan in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund. ſecunde. q. <hi>184.</hi> art. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epiſcopus legitimè iurare poteſt Homagium quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam vel fidelitatem, quia nil in iſto iuramento continetur, circa curam animarum;</hi> for that is taken in relation to their temporalls which they haue from the Kings favours; not in relation to their conſecration, which they haue from the qualifying grace of God, which was well expreſſed anciently in their ſtile <hi>[Dei gratiâ Epiſcopus]</hi> and now by <hi>[providentia divinâ,]</hi> ſo that ſeeing they perform the ſame ſervices, they may enjoy the ſame priviledges with the Barons. Now as all priviledges, ſo theſe that they enjoy common with them, are beſides and aboue the common courſe of law. For inſtance, as they are Aſſeſſors in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they may appeare by Proxie; as they are witneſſes, they may ſweare onely <hi>Viſis Evangeliis, verbo ſacerdotis;</hi> as Barons, by their honour; and when they are at any time Delinquents, they ſhould bee tried by their Peeres, (if they were tried as Biſhops, and not firſt degraded;) and ſo ſome haue beene tried, vntill one appealed from them to the Pope. And good reaſon in thoſe dayes they had, (if not now) to bee ſo tried, becauſe many of the Biſhops of thoſe times were of the Princes of the nobilitie; (as may be ſeene in Biſhop <hi>Godwins</hi> Catalogue of Biſhops:) ſo that when Peeres were Biſhops, why ſhould not Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:10388:52"/> bee Peeres. It ſeemes in <hi>Richard</hi> the ſeconds dayes they were ſo accounted, for when hee did make vp the number of the twelue Peeres of the land, he choſe <hi>Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Exeter</hi> one of them, which (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) hee would not haue done if hee had not beene a Peere before: and I am the rather perſwaded ſo to thinke, becauſe <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond extends the ſtatute of <hi>Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum magnatum,</hi> to Biſhops as well as Dukes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Rich</hi>
               </note> Earles and Barons vnder the title of Peeres of the land. Beſides theſe priviledges which they haue as they are Barons, the Kings of this land haue beene pleaſed out of their Princely favours to beſtow many freedomes vpon them, eſpecially on the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> as amongſt other ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and knowne,<note place="margin">Stamfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rogat. c.</note> one againſt his Majeſties written pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, as that the land held of that Biſhop ſhall not be Ward to the King. And I beleeue the high eſtimation of that See abroad might mooue them to it, for they are not onely ſtiled Primates of all <hi>England,</hi> and Metropolitans,<note place="margin">Duaren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gradibus cap. <hi>9.</hi> Laelius Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtatu Leg</note> but Patriarches; <hi>Patriarchae minorum gentium ſunt Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarienſis, Aquilienſis, Biturgienſis, &amp; Gradenſis,</hi> and the moſt lawfull Legats of the Apoſtolicall See: <hi>Legati nati dignitas Archiepiſcopatui Cantuarienſi, Remenſi, Eboracenſi, &amp; Piſano annexa eſt.</hi> This forraine reſpect might mooue them more particularly to honour them, though they haue alwayes moſt highly favoured Biſhops in generall, in ſomuch, that they haue made them not onely <hi>á ſacris,</hi> but <hi>à ſecretis,</hi> which is ſafe for a King, and no diſtraction to a Biſhop in his calling;<note place="margin">Lipſius A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3.</hi> Polit.</note> with <hi>Lipſius</hi> limitation <hi>intereſſe eos poſſe imò debere, ſed rarenter cùm de rebus planè ſeriis agitur, &amp; quae tangunt vniverſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſtatum;</hi> then ſhould not Princes need to forbid Biſhops the Court without they were ſent for, (as <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> was faine to doe). Thus I haue brifely diſcourſed,<note place="margin">Baron. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Anno <hi>528</hi>
               </note> though not fully diſcovered ſome thing of the relation betwixt the ſtate
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:10388:53"/> Eccleſiaſticall and the Civill; which I haue done without adviſing in any thing to an alteration, or deviſing any thing for innovation; and with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the licence of authority and the judgement of the learned.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10388:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
